<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://melaniewalsh.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://melaniewalsh.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-11-11T16:16:12+00:00</updated><id>https://melaniewalsh.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Assistant Professor at UW in Seattle. Data science, digital humanities, literature, culture. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Using Social Media Data in Research—Whether You’re in English Lit or Information Science</title><link href="https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2023/social-media-research/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Using Social Media Data in Research—Whether You’re in English Lit or Information Science"/><published>2023-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2023/social-media-research</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2023/social-media-research/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p>I’m excited to share that my essay, <a href="https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/f3f87448-138c-4d19-8ff8-b06acf40ddd1/section/a57b98ab-0f10-45d0-b205-3e563aab7ea8#ch18">“The Challenges and Possibilities of Social Media Data: New Directions in Literary Studies and the Digital Humanities,”</a> was just published open-access in the latest volume of <a href="https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/debates-in-the-digital-humanities-2023/section/708b9ac7-b96f-4059-8534-a1400e9601e9#toc"><em>Debates in the Digital Humanities 2023</em></a>.</p> <p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*WMnaeeiGQfLtni7b_vTm3Q.png" alt=""/></p> <p>In this essay, I write about two things:</p> <ol> <li>how book-related social media data (e.g., Goodreads ratings, BookTok videos, fanfiction stories, r/books Reddit memes) has enabled all kinds of cool new research related to contemporary readers, literature, and culture;</li> <li>how social media data also seriously challenges traditional ways of doing research—especially but not exclusively in the humanities and literary studies—and how it demands new approaches and considerations of user privacy and ethics.</li> </ol> <p>If you’re interested in readers, reception, or how scholars are using digital humanities approaches to study the life of texts, I hope you’ll check out <a href="https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/f3f87448-138c-4d19-8ff8-b06acf40ddd1/section/a57b98ab-0f10-45d0-b205-3e563aab7ea8#ch18">my full <em>Debates in the Digital Humanities</em> essay</a>. In the first half of the essay, I sketch out the DH subfield of “computational reception studies” and show how social media data resembles earlier forms of reception data featured in DH work, such as <a href="https://culturalanalytics.org/article/11038">19th-century library checkout records</a> and <a href="https://tedunderwood.github.io/badpublicity/">20th-century book reviews</a>.</p> <p>But in this blog post, I want to briefly summarize a few of <strong>my main recommendations for working with, sharing, and citing social media data in research</strong> because I get asked about these issues a lot.</p> <p>I also want to address a couple of major developments in the social media world that have taken place since I finalized copyedits on the essay in October 2022 — like the takeover of Twitter by a̶ ̶r̶i̶g̶h̶t̶-̶w̶i̶n̶g̶ ̶t̶r̶o̶l̶l̶ Elon Musk, who quickly <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/5/31/23739084/twitter-elon-musk-api-policy-chilling-academic-research">shuttered the Academic Twitter API</a>, and who <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/3/30/23662832/twitter-api-tiers-free-bot-novelty-accounts-basic-enterprice-monthly-price">made the regular Twitter API so expensive</a> that it’s basically shuttered, too.</p> <p>These changes have <a href="https://sites.google.com/umich.edu/postapiconference/post-api-2023?authuser=0">rocked the social media research community</a>, and they complicate at least one of my recommendations in the essay, so I wanted to provide an update on my thinking and the state-of-the-field here.</p> <p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*JVVLjOk2Ewhtyq81xqAtrw.png" alt=""/></p> <p><em>via <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/5/31/23739084/twitter-elon-musk-api-policy-chilling-academic-research">The Verge</a></em></p> <p>Most of my recommendations for working with social media data are collated from or inspired by the work of other researchers I admire — including Moya Bailey, Sarah J. Jackson, and Brooke Foucault Welles; Deen Freelon, Charlton D. McIlwain, and Meredith D. Clark; Dorothy Kim and Eunsong Kim; Brianna Dym and Casey Fiesler; and members of the <a href="https://www.docnow.io/">Documenting the Now</a> project.</p> <p>The reason that these researchers and the best practices that they espouse or model in their work are so important is because <strong>there aren’t clear laws or guidelines that dictate how you’re supposed to work with social media data responsibly</strong>.¹</p> <p>IRBs, or institutional review boards, are administrative bodies that evaluate and approve the ethical dimensions of research involving human participants (IRBs are required at U.S. institutions that receive federal research money; institutions outside the U.S. have their own equivalents), but IRBs have mostly washed their hands of social media research. They’ve largely determined that, if the social media data is “public,” <a href="https://irb.upenn.edu/homepage/social-behavioral-homepage/guidance/types-of-social-behavioral-research/use-of-social-media-as-a-research-activity/#:~:text=Please%20be%20especially%20mindful%20when,and%20other%20image%2Dbased%20content.&amp;text=Use%20of%20private%20social%20media%20data%20requires%20IRB%20review.">then the research falls outside their purview</a>.</p> <p><strong>Do you need IRB approval to work with social media data?</strong> is one of the most common questions that I hear from people who are new to this area. And the answer to that question is basically: <strong>it depends; it’s safest to apply and get an exemption; but <em>probably no</em></strong>.</p> <p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*rCRl5acaBldSLiM-xSNp-A.png" alt=""/></p> <p><em><a href="https://irb.upenn.edu/homepage/social-behavioral-homepage/guidance/types-of-social-behavioral-research/use-of-social-media-as-a-research-activity/#:~:text=Please%20be%20especially%20mindful%20when,and%20other%20image-based%20content.&amp;text=Use%20of%20private%20social%20media%20data%20requires%20IRB%20review.">Penn Social Behavioral Research</a> on social media data and IRBs</em></p> <p>When I first started doing social media research (collecting <a href="https://tweetsofanativeson.com/Publications/">tweets about the writer James Baldwin</a> with the Twitter API), I was a few years into an English Literature PhD program, and I felt especially lost about the best ways to collect and share tweets or cite them in published articles, because literature professors don’t often do “human subject” research or work with IRBs or include this kind of training in their graduate programs. But since the IRB has largely abdicated its responsibility with regard to social media research, it turned out that social scientists and scientists were basically in the same boat, too. And we’re all still in that boat.</p> <p>That’s why I’ve chosen to turn to the model of the scholars and projects mentioned above and discussed below. I believe that these researchers and their work are particularly useful not only because their work is exemplary but also because their work focuses on the data of marginalized or otherwise vulnerable communities, such as Black activists and LBGTQ fanfiction writers. Centering research on these communities can, I think, help us develop social media research best practices that consider the experiences of those disproportionately subject to risk online as a baseline.</p> <h2 id="how-should-researchers-engage-with-the-online-communities-whose-data-they-computationally-collect-and-analyze">How should researchers engage with the online communities whose data they computationally collect and analyze?</h2> <p>As <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2023/06/28/openai-chatgpt-lawsuit-class-action/">OpenAI’s massive scrape of internet data</a> has proven, it’s not only possible but incredibly common for companies, researchers, and regular people to collect users’ personal data without their permission and knowledge. Equally worrisome, it’s just as common for the same parties to lack knowledge about the users whose data they collect.</p> <p>As Bergis Jules, Ed Summers, and Vernon Mitchell put it in <a href="https://www.docnow.io/docs/docnow-whitepaper-2018.pdf">their white paper</a> for Documenting the Now (a project that helps develop tools and practices for ethically archiving social media data):</p> <blockquote> <p>the internet affords the luxury of a certain amount of distance to be able to observe people, consume information generated by and about them, and collect their data without having to participate in equitable engagement as a way to understand their lives, communities, or concerns.</p> </blockquote> <p>For these reasons, they and other scholars argue that <strong>researchers should engage with and be knowledgeable about the communities whom they are studying and collecting data from </strong>— whether through conversation, collaboration, interviews, or ethnographic approaches.</p> <p>By directly engaging with online communities, researchers can make better, more informed, and more context-dependent decisions about other parts of the research process, such as whether to cite a specific user in a published article (more on that below).</p> <p>For example, in Brianna Dym and Casey Fiesler’s <a href="https://journal.transformativeworks.org/index.php/twc/article/view/1733/2445">extremely useful best practices for studying online fandom data</a>, they recommend that researchers who are not familiar with fan communities “spend time [in online fandom spaces] and take the time to talk to fans and to understand and learn their norms,” not only to learn more about the community but also to become more “mindful of each user’s reasonable expectations of privacy, which may be dependent on the community or platform.”</p> <p>They further underscore that making connections with individual users is possible even for large-scale, data-driven research:</p> <blockquote> <p>Even for public data sets in which individual participants might number in the tens of thousands to the millions, it might be possible to talk to some members of the target population in order to better understand what values and concerns people might hold that would deter them from consenting to their data being used.</p> </blockquote> <p>Here are a few concrete examples of this kind of mixed-methods (quantitative/qualitative) approach to studying and engaging with social media communities in action:</p> <ol> <li>In Moya Bailey’s <a href="https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/9/2/000209/000209.html">research on the hashtag #GirlsLikeUs</a>, which was created by trans advocate Janet Mock, Bailey sought Mock’s permission to work on the project before it began, and she collaborated with Mock to develop her research questions and determine the project’s direction. Though Bailey’s research included data collection and quantitative analyses, it was also shaped by a consenting collaborator who was part of the community being studied.</li> <li>In Bailey’s 2020 book with Sarah J. Jackson and Brooke Foucault Welles, <a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262043373/hashtagactivism/"><em>#HashtagActivism: Networks of Race and Gender</em></a>, they similarly frame social media users as collaborators, and they pair each chapter of the book with “an essay written by an influential member of a particular hashtag activism network.”</li> <li>Along similar lines, Deen Freelon, Charlton McIlwain, and Meredith Clark used large-scale network analysis techniques to study 40 million #BlackLivesMatter (BLM) tweets in their report <a href="https://cmsimpact.org/resource/beyond-hashtags-ferguson-blacklivesmatter-online-struggle-offline-justice/">“Beyond the hashtags: #Ferguson, #Blacklivesmatter, and the online struggle for offline justice.”</a> But they also interviewed and talked to dozens of BLM activists and allies “to better understand their thoughts about how social media was and was not useful in their work.”</li> </ol> <h2 id="how-should-researchers-cite-social-media-users-in-published-research">How should researchers cite social media users in published research?</h2> <p>If you want to include or quote a social media post in your published article, <strong>should you</strong> <strong>cite the author, anonymize the author, paraphrase the post, or do something else?</strong> This is another common question that I hear as a social media researcher, and I think it’s an especially important one for humanities scholars, who often include and analyze specific examples of texts in their work (as opposed to computer science researchers, for example, who often work with aggregated representations of data).</p> <p>Before going any further, I want to head off anyone who’s about to spout <strong>the erroneous but distressingly common argument that you can do whatever you want with social media data if it’s “public”</strong> — that is, if it’s published openly on the internet by a public account. Dym and Fieseler (and many other scholars) have <a href="https://journal.transformativeworks.org/index.php/twc/article/view/1733/2445">worked hard</a> to show that this argument is a load of hooey (as my grandma would say). They argue that privacy on the internet is <em>contextual</em>. Your expectation of privacy on Twitter (or X) is going to be very different if you’re a celebrity versus a regular person with 50 followers. And violating those expectations can have serious consequences, as I’ll explain below.</p> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">I helped <a href="https://twitter.com/cfiesler?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@cfiesler</a> make memes for her ethics class and came up with this gem <a href="https://t.co/zGUYPtusaQ">pic.twitter.com/zGUYPtusaQ</a></p>&mdash; Dr. Brianna Dym (@BriannaDym) <a href="https://twitter.com/BriannaDym/status/1220440276579373057?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 23, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <p><em>I showed this meme to my students, and now it lives rent-free in my brain.</em></p> <p>So if you’re including or quoting users’ posts in published scholarship, coming up with a citation strategy is imperative.</p> <p><strong>Many people think that anonymizing social media posts is a good citation strategy that protects users’ privacy. But it’s not.</strong>“Even when anonymized by not including usernames, content from social media collected and shared in research articles can be easily traced back to its creator,” as Dym and Fiesler assert, drawing on a <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41746-018-0036-2">study by John W. Ayers and colleagues</a>. Basically, you can google the text of a social media post and find the original post, context, and its author extremely easily.</p> <p>The other big problem with anonymization is that it robs users of authorship. <strong>Creators deserve intellectual credit</strong> <strong>for what they create and publish</strong>, as <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1023/A:1021316409277">Amy Bruckman and others have maintained</a>.</p> <p>So, anonymizing posts is not a good strategy, and explicitly citing the author of a post is ideal. But citation can be tricky, too. In some cases, it can even be dangerous to cite authors, especially if you do so without their knowledge and permission. Why? <strong>Because citing social media users in a new context can expose them to new and unexpected audiences, which can lead to unwanted attention, harassment, doxxing, personal and professional complications, and other negative outcomes.</strong></p> <p>For example, the Documenting the Now project—which has led social media archiving efforts related to the Ferguson protests, Black Lives Matter, and other social movements—discusses how <a href="https://www.docnow.io/docs/docnow-whitepaper-2018.pdf.">“activists of color . . . face a disproportionate level of harm from surveillance and data collection by law enforcement,”</a> and thus amplifying their words or actions (as documented through social media) might put them in danger, even more so than the average social media user.</p> <p>In a similar vein, when Dym and Fiesler asked LGBTQ fanfiction writers and those with LGBTQ friends in the community how they felt about researchers or journalists citing their stories, they expressed many concerns, including the concern that “exposing fandom content to a broader audience could lead to fans being accidentally outed.”</p> <p>For these reasons, <strong>researchers who wish to cite specific social media posts in published research should make their best effort to contact the authors and seek explicit permission to use the posts.</strong> But there are exceptions. If a user is a public figure, like Joe Biden, or if a post has already reached a wide public audience, like a viral TikTok video, then I personally don’t think that getting direct permission is necessary. However, it can be difficult to draw a line about who counts as a public figure or what counts as reaching a “wide public audience.”</p> <p>In their <a href="https://cmsimpact.org/resource/beyond-hashtags-ferguson-blacklivesmatter-online-struggle-offline-justice/">“Beyond the Hashtags” report</a>, Freelon, McIlwain, and Clark offer a few concrete examples of these <strong>“reasonably public” thresholds</strong> (as I like to think of them). Freelon et al. chose to only cite tweets that met at least one of the following criteria: the tweet had been <strong>retweeted more than 100 times</strong>; the tweet had been published by an <strong>officially verified Twitter account</strong>; and/or the tweet had been published by a <strong>Twitter account with more than 3,000 followers</strong> (placing a user in the top one-percent of the most followed Twitter accounts at that time). Additionally, they did not include the actual text of tweets in their report and <strong>only included links to the tweets</strong>, essentially enabling users to delete their tweets and remove themselves from the study. Devising these kinds of thresholds can be challenging and very subjective, but they can also be helpful for guiding the focus of a study away from obscure content and toward matters of genuine public interest and concern.</p> <p>Frustratingly, Elon Musk’s drastic changes to Twitter have also impacted researchers’ ability to devise some of these thresholds, since he <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2023/04/24/tech/musk-twitter-blue-check-mark/index.html">radically altered X’s “verified” user system</a>. While in the past Twitter would “verify” a user by internally determining that their account was of “public interest” (a process that had its own flaws, to be clear), now this status is exclusively offered to users who pay for an <a href="https://help.twitter.com/en/managing-your-account/about-x-verified-accounts">X Premium monthly subscription</a>. So today, X’s verification system doesn’t tell you anything except who’s paying for X.</p> <p>Sometimes, of course, there are cases when a researcher might want to include a social media post in a publication, but it does not meet these reasonably public thresholds, and its author cannot be reached for comment or to grant permission. What to do then? In these cases, Dym and Fiesler recommend <strong>paraphrasing posts</strong> in such a way that they are not traceable back to the original post or <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/1369118X.2011.641993"><strong>ethically “fabricating” material</strong></a> in ways that Annette Markham has advocated and described, such as by <strong>creating a composite account of a person, interaction, or dialogue</strong>. These strategies may seem foreign and potentially even a little blasphemous to some humanities scholars, especially those who are trained to attend closely to texts and all their nuances. But if these adaptations are necessary to protect users in a given situation, then they obviously need to be embraced. (Basically, lit scholars, we will need to get over ourselves.)</p> <p><strong>What about if you’re studying social media users who you are critical of, such as fascists or white supremacists?</strong> This a question that I did not address in my <em>Debates in the Digital Humanities</em> essay, but I just wanted to raise it briefly here because I think it’s super important. In many ways, I think the best practices I’ve outlined above could still be applied successfully in these cases. If a post is shared by a prominent figure or has reached a wide audience, it’s fair game, and if it doesn’t reach those thresholds, and you can’t get in touch (or don’t want to get in touch) with the author of the post, perhaps you could paraphrase it. (Because of course it could be dangerous to directly contact a fascist or white supremacist and notify them about your involvement in research scrutinizing their behavior and beliefs, and it could be particularly dangerous depending on your identity.) But should you cite the author of such a social media post in full without the author’s permission just because you disagree with them or even disavow them? I’m not sure. Perhaps you could make the case that studying fascist or white supremacist online communities (or whatever communities) is such a matter of public significance that it would justify this choice, that its significance might be akin to a post having reached a wide public audience. But again, I’m not sure. This is an issue that I continue to struggle with, and I would love to hear more about what other people think and what strategies people have developed to address these issues.</p> <h2 id="how-if-at-all-should-researchers-share-users-data">How, if at all, should researchers share users’ data?</h2> <p>While sharing data is a vitally important part of the research process—enabling reproducibility, enhancing evaluation, and increasing accessibility—sharing social media datasets in responsible ways can be very challenging. Social media datasets contain a lot of potentially identifiable information about users, so sharing this kind of data is often explicitly prohibited by platforms’ Terms of Service, and beyond that (because of course we don’t let platforms tell us what’s ethical and what’s not) it’s often considered a privacy violation that can lead to negative consequences for users, such as doxxing, harassment, and other adverse outcomes like those discussed above.</p> <p>One potential strategy for mitigating these harms is to <strong>share social media datasets in ways that enable users’ “right to be forgotten</strong>”—that is, to enable users to remove themselves from the dataset whenever they want. Usually, this means introducing some kind of time lag into the dataset sharing/retrieval process. For example, a researcher might share the code that they used to scrape TikTok posts but not the posts themselves, enabling others to recreate the dataset but not include any posts that have been deleted or removed.</p> <p>Perhaps the best known and most institutionally supported example of this kind of approach was Twitter’s “tweet ID” sharing format—<strong>a format that Elon Musk has virtually destroyed since I published my <em>Debates in DH</em> essay.</strong> A tweet ID is a unique identifier that is associated with every single tweet that’s ever been tweeted. Basically, it’s a unique string of numbers — e.g., <a href="https://twitter.com/icecube/status/1702444061657841919"><em>1702444061657841919</em></a> —that links back to a full, richly embodied tweet, with its text, author, URL, publication date, images/videos, and all its other juicy metadata.</p> <p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*Wt50O_2qjSTW2FixI2cDug.png" alt=""/></p> <p><em><a href="https://archive.org/details/toni-morrison-tweets">A list of tweet ids</a></em></p> <p>Before Musk’s takeover of the platform, you could pass a list of tweet IDs to the Twitter API and download full datasets for the tweets that they referenced—a process known as “hydrating” tweets. The most important part was that you could only download data for tweets that still existed. Because a tweet ID will only link back to a tweet if it has not been deleted or if its account has not been made private or suspended, etc. For these reasons, Ed Summers, the technical lead of the Documenting the Now project, has suggested that <a href="https://medium.com/on-archivy/on-forgetting-e01a2b95272">tweet IDs advance an implicit ethical position</a> by allowing users “to exercise their right to be forgotten.” By deleting a tweet or making their account private, users can remove themselves from all future versions of the data.</p> <p>Twitter’s policies have long forbidden people from publicly sharing full datasets of tweets, but it has allowed people to openly share tweet IDs. And until recently (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20231118053057/https://developer.twitter.com/en/developer-terms/policy#4-e">as recently as November 18, 2023</a>), academics were even explicitly permitted to share as many tweet IDs as they wanted:</p> <blockquote> <p><em>If you provide Twitter Content to third parties, including downloadable datasets or via an API</em><strong><em>, you may only distribute Tweet IDs, Direct Message IDs, and/or User IDs</em></strong> <em>(except as described below).</em> <strong><em>We also grant special permissions to academic researchers sharing Tweet IDs and User IDs for non-commercial research purposes.</em></strong></p> </blockquote> <blockquote> <p><em>In total, you may not distribute more than 1,500,000 Tweet IDs to any entity…within any 30 day period unless you have received written permission from Twitter…</em><strong><em>Academic researchers are permitted to distribute an unlimited number of Tweet IDs</em></strong> <em>and/or User IDs if they are doing so on behalf of an academic institution and for the sole purpose of non-commercial research.</em></p> </blockquote> <p>Because of this institutional support and its inherent “right to be forgotten” capacities, many researchers chose to share their data as tweet IDs in the last decade or so. The DocNow project even created a <a href="https://catalog.docnow.io/">catalog of tweet IDs</a>, which now hosts more than 7 billion of them—linking back to full Twitter datasets about COVID, Donald Trump, Toni Morrison, natural disasters, celebrities, protest movements, the alt-right, and many other important subjects. Summers also created a widely-used GUI application called <a href="https://github.com/DocNow/hydrator">“Hydrator,”</a> which conveniently allowed people to download tweets from lists of tweet IDs via the API but without ever touching the command line or writing a single line of code.</p> <p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*JFZVbhfp_8GBKto9asYozw.png" alt=""/></p> <p><em>DocNow Catalog (<a href="https://catalog.docnow.io/">https://catalog.docnow.io/</a>)</em></p> <p>But today, sadly, Musk’s dismantling of the API and other radical policy changes have robbed DocNow’s incredible Catalog and Hydrator app and even their <a href="https://twarc-project.readthedocs.io/en/latest/">Twitter collection tool twarc</a> of much of their usefulness. (The DocNow team has written about <a href="https://medium.com/documenting-docnow/looking-forwards-64cee8436640">the demise of these tools here</a>, offering their own perspective on paths forward.) Because today, with the current <a href="https://developer.twitter.com/en/docs/twitter-api/getting-started/about-twitter-api#item0">“Free” tier of the Twitter API</a>, you can’t hydrate any tweet IDs at all. And with the <a href="https://developer.twitter.com/en/docs/twitter-api/getting-started/about-twitter-api#item0">$100-a-month “Basic” tier</a> and the <a href="https://developer.twitter.com/en/docs/twitter-api/getting-started/about-twitter-api#item0">$5,000-a-month “Pro” tier</a>, you can only retrieve (“pull”) 10,000 tweets and 1 million tweets per month, respectively. This is a severe curtailing of what used to be possible. Seven years ago, when I was a graduate student, I was able to hydrate 30 million tweets in under a week with only free access to the Twitter API. The <a href="https://dfreelon.org/2017/01/03/beyond-the-hashtags-twitter-data/">tweet IDs that I hydrated</a> were publicly shared by Freelon, McIlwain, and Clark from their “Beyond the Hashtags” report, and their generous data sharing was what made it possible for me to do the research that would become my first published article. I didn’t have the funding or capacity at the time to get this data in any other way. And it’s sad to me that today’s graduate students, as well as other researchers with limited funding, will not be able to benefit from the same kind of data sharing.</p> <p>In addition to the severe curtailing of the API, X also recently (again very recently, since November 18, 2023) <a href="https://developer.twitter.com/en/developer-terms/policy#4-e">changed its developer policy</a> with regard to tweet IDs (which they now call “post IDs”). Academics are no longer permitted to share as many post IDs as they want, and in fact there are new clauses that suggest that, before sharing post IDs, X <a href="https://developer.twitter.com/en/developer-terms/policy#4-e">must explicitly approve of the research related to the post IDs in writing</a> (unclear if this approval includes having previously been approved for a Academic Twitter API account):</p> <blockquote> <p><em>If you provide</em> <strong><em>X Content</em></strong> <em>to third parties, including downloadable datasets or via an API, you may only distribute</em> <strong><em>Post IDs</em></strong><em>, Direct Message IDs, and/or User IDs (except as described below).</em></p> </blockquote> <blockquote> <p><em>In total, you may not distribute more than 1,500,000 Post IDs to any entity…within any 30 day period unless you have received written permission from X….Academic researchers are permitted to distribute Post IDs and/or User IDs solely for the purposes of non-commercial research on behalf of an academic institution, and</em> <strong><em>that has been approved by X in writing, or peer review or validation of such research. Only as many Post IDs or User IDs that is necessary for such research, and has been approved by X may be used.</em></strong></p> </blockquote> <p>So what will become of the billions of tweet IDs shared by researchers that are now basically inaccessible through the API? And how else can we responsibly share Twitter data — or other kinds of social media data?</p> <p>Another strategy for sharing social media datasets is <strong>to use institutional repositories like the new</strong> <a href="https://socialmediaarchive.org/pages/?page=About&amp;ln=en"><strong>Social Media Archive</strong></a> <strong>(SOMAR)</strong>, housed by the <a href="https://www.icpsr.umich.edu/">Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research</a> (ICPSR) at the University of Michigan. SOMAR is promising because it allows researchers to place restrictions on the datasets that they share, so it’s possible to deposit and share a social media dataset but require anybody who wishes to access the data <a href="https://somar.infoready4.com/#">to submit an application that might include</a>: proof of affiliation with an academic institution and a terminal degree, a summary of the research that they intend to do, proof of IRB approval from their own institution, a signed restricted data agreement, and more. Additionally, when depositing data into SOMAR, researchers can choose to restrict access to a <a href="https://socialmediaarchive.org/pages/?page=FAQs&amp;ln=en">Virtual Data Enclave (VDE)</a>, so that others can’t actually download the data or take the data anywhere beyond the platform. (It’s also possible to make data publicly available for direct download, or to make data available for direct download with only a login to a SOMAR account.) So perhaps researchers who previously shared their Twitter data as tweet IDs on the DocNow Catalog might instead deposit their Twitter datasets into SOMAR with appropriate restrictions.</p> <p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*hbx30I_VxGt8kpg_gyn8rw.png" alt=""/></p> <p><em>SOMAR (<a href="https://socialmediaarchive.org/">https://socialmediaarchive.org/</a>)</em></p> <p>Interestingly, SOMAR is also supported by <a href="https://www.icpsr.umich.edu/web/about/cms/4081">a $1.3 million gift from Meta</a>, and Meta has just unveiled a <a href="https://transparency.fb.com/researchtools/meta-content-library">new academic research API</a> that is exclusively available through SOMAR’s Virtual Data Enclave (VDE). They also announced that ICPSR and SOMAR will <a href="https://www.icpsr.umich.edu/web/about/cms/5231">handle all of the applications</a> for research access to Meta’s new API. This partnership introduces a new model for academic social media research, attempting to close the gap between Big Tech social media and the academy, and eliminating the need to share data by never letting the data leave in the first place. The fact that Meta has so much unilateral power in determining what data researchers can access through this API/platform—as well as what researchers can do with that data—is concerning. When Meta has provided data to researchers in the past and asked researchers to trust them without transparency, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/live/2020/2020-election-misinformation-distortions#facebook-sent-flawed-data-to-misinformation-researchers">it has <em>not</em> worked out well</a>. But who knows what will happen with this new partnership.</p> <p>Despite these concerns, I am still interested in and curious about SOMAR’s future. The repository addresses a pressing need in the field that is not being addressed in very many other places. Of course, there are additional drawbacks to sharing data in repositories like SOMAR. For example, some of the restrictions that can be placed on data are exclusionary to those who are not academic researchers with terminal degrees, likely making some data unavailable to the communities who actually created it. (Enabling communities to access and control their own data has long been a goal of the DocNow project, and they recently wrote about the benefits of diversifying <a href="https://medium.com/documenting-docnow/looking-forwards-64cee8436640">“who can use web and social media archiving tools to create data collections…beyond academic researchers and the handful of archivists at academic and national libraries”</a>). Also, these kinds of dataset deposits do not inherently enable users’ right to be forgotten as some other data sharing approaches do. But for now, it is still better than most alternatives (like openly publishing sensitive user data or allowing valuable archives of social movements to die on old computers), so I think it’s worth paying attention to.</p> <hr/> <p>The world of social media changes rapidly, as the last year has shown us. (I mean, for real, providing updates on all of Elon Musk’s antics has made this update almost as long as my original essay.) To keep pace, the conversation about working with social media data will need to change and evolve, too. But I think the model demonstrated by the researchers discussed above—which emphasizes actual engagement and conversation with social media users, explicit permission with regard to quotation and citation of posts, responsible data sharing practices, and a prioritization of the most vulnerable—can provide a solid foundation for the future. And in that future, I think that researchers will need to be sure to develop social media data infrastructures and approaches that are distinct from, and even explicitly opposed to Big Tech platforms, even as we find ourselves sometimes necessarily collaborating with them.</p> <p><strong>Footnotes</strong></p> <p>1: Some professional academic organizations, like the <a href="https://aoir.org/">Association of Internet Researchers</a> (AoIR), have published guidelines for working with internet data: <a href="https://aoir.org/ethics/">https://aoir.org/ethics/</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="twitter"/><category term="social-media"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Recommendations for working with, citing, and sharing social media data in research — with updates after Elon Musks' Twitter takeover]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://melaniewalsh.org/%7B%22thumb%22=%3E%22../images/banner-purple.png%22%7D"/><media:content medium="image" url="https://melaniewalsh.org/%7B%22thumb%22=%3E%22../images/banner-purple.png%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"/></entry><entry><title type="html">Embed an Interactive Plot with ggplot, plotly, &amp;amp; RStudio</title><link href="https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2022/embedding-interactive-viz/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Embed an Interactive Plot with ggplot, plotly, &amp;amp; RStudio"/><published>2022-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2022/embedding-interactive-viz</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2022/embedding-interactive-viz/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <p>I’m excited to share that my essay, <a href="https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/f3f87448-138c-4d19-8ff8-b06acf40ddd1/section/a57b98ab-0f10-45d0-b205-3e563aab7ea8#ch18">“The Challenges and Possibilities of Social Media Data: New Directions in Literary Studies and the Digital Humanities,”</a> was just published open-access in the latest volume of <a href="https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/debates-in-the-digital-humanities-2023/section/708b9ac7-b96f-4059-8534-a1400e9601e9#toc"><em>Debates in the Digital Humanities 2023</em></a>.</p> <p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*WMnaeeiGQfLtni7b_vTm3Q.png" alt=""/></p> <p>In this essay, I write about two things:</p> <ol> <li>how book-related social media data (e.g., Goodreads ratings, BookTok videos, fanfiction stories, r/books Reddit memes) has enabled all kinds of cool new research related to contemporary readers, literature, and culture;</li> <li>how social media data also seriously challenges traditional ways of doing research—especially but not exclusively in the humanities and literary studies—and how it demands new approaches and considerations of user privacy and ethics.</li> </ol> <p>If you’re interested in readers, reception, or how scholars are using digital humanities approaches to study the life of texts, I hope you’ll check out <a href="https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/f3f87448-138c-4d19-8ff8-b06acf40ddd1/section/a57b98ab-0f10-45d0-b205-3e563aab7ea8#ch18">my full <em>Debates in the Digital Humanities</em> essay</a>. In the first half of the essay, I sketch out the DH subfield of “computational reception studies” and show how social media data resembles earlier forms of reception data featured in DH work, such as <a href="https://culturalanalytics.org/article/11038">19th-century library checkout records</a> and <a href="https://tedunderwood.github.io/badpublicity/">20th-century book reviews</a>.</p> <p>But in this blog post, I want to briefly summarize a few of <strong>my main recommendations for working with, sharing, and citing social media data in research</strong> because I get asked about these issues a lot.</p> <p>I also want to address a couple of major developments in the social media world that have taken place since I finalized copyedits on the essay in October 2022 — like the takeover of Twitter by a̶ ̶r̶i̶g̶h̶t̶-̶w̶i̶n̶g̶ ̶t̶r̶o̶l̶l̶ Elon Musk, who quickly <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/5/31/23739084/twitter-elon-musk-api-policy-chilling-academic-research">shuttered the Academic Twitter API</a>, and who <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/3/30/23662832/twitter-api-tiers-free-bot-novelty-accounts-basic-enterprice-monthly-price">made the regular Twitter API so expensive</a> that it’s basically shuttered, too.</p> <p>These changes have <a href="https://sites.google.com/umich.edu/postapiconference/post-api-2023?authuser=0">rocked the social media research community</a>, and they complicate at least one of my recommendations in the essay, so I wanted to provide an update on my thinking and the state-of-the-field here.</p> <p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*JVVLjOk2Ewhtyq81xqAtrw.png" alt=""/></p> <p><em>via <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/5/31/23739084/twitter-elon-musk-api-policy-chilling-academic-research">The Verge</a></em></p> <p>Most of my recommendations for working with social media data are collated from or inspired by the work of other researchers I admire — including Moya Bailey, Sarah J. Jackson, and Brooke Foucault Welles; Deen Freelon, Charlton D. McIlwain, and Meredith D. Clark; Dorothy Kim and Eunsong Kim; Brianna Dym and Casey Fiesler; and members of the <a href="https://www.docnow.io/">Documenting the Now</a> project.</p> <p>The reason that these researchers and the best practices that they espouse or model in their work are so important is because <strong>there aren’t clear laws or guidelines that dictate how you’re supposed to work with social media data responsibly</strong>.¹</p> <p>IRBs, or institutional review boards, are administrative bodies that evaluate and approve the ethical dimensions of research involving human participants (IRBs are required at U.S. institutions that receive federal research money; institutions outside the U.S. have their own equivalents), but IRBs have mostly washed their hands of social media research. They’ve largely determined that, if the social media data is “public,” <a href="https://irb.upenn.edu/homepage/social-behavioral-homepage/guidance/types-of-social-behavioral-research/use-of-social-media-as-a-research-activity/#:~:text=Please%20be%20especially%20mindful%20when,and%20other%20image%2Dbased%20content.&amp;text=Use%20of%20private%20social%20media%20data%20requires%20IRB%20review.">then the research falls outside their purview</a>.</p> <p><strong>Do you need IRB approval to work with social media data?</strong> is one of the most common questions that I hear from people who are new to this area. And the answer to that question is basically: <strong>it depends; it’s safest to apply and get an exemption; but <em>probably no</em></strong>.</p> <p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*rCRl5acaBldSLiM-xSNp-A.png" alt=""/></p> <p><em><a href="https://irb.upenn.edu/homepage/social-behavioral-homepage/guidance/types-of-social-behavioral-research/use-of-social-media-as-a-research-activity/#:~:text=Please%20be%20especially%20mindful%20when,and%20other%20image-based%20content.&amp;text=Use%20of%20private%20social%20media%20data%20requires%20IRB%20review.">Penn Social Behavioral Research</a> on social media data and IRBs</em></p> <p>When I first started doing social media research (collecting <a href="https://tweetsofanativeson.com/Publications/">tweets about the writer James Baldwin</a> with the Twitter API), I was a few years into an English Literature PhD program, and I felt especially lost about the best ways to collect and share tweets or cite them in published articles, because literature professors don’t often do “human subject” research or work with IRBs or include this kind of training in their graduate programs. But since the IRB has largely abdicated its responsibility with regard to social media research, it turned out that social scientists and scientists were basically in the same boat, too. And we’re all still in that boat.</p> <p>That’s why I’ve chosen to turn to the model of the scholars and projects mentioned above and discussed below. I believe that these researchers and their work are particularly useful not only because their work is exemplary but also because their work focuses on the data of marginalized or otherwise vulnerable communities, such as Black activists and LBGTQ fanfiction writers. Centering research on these communities can, I think, help us develop social media research best practices that consider the experiences of those disproportionately subject to risk online as a baseline.</p> <h2 id="how-should-researchers-engage-with-the-online-communities-whose-data-they-computationally-collect-and-analyze">How should researchers engage with the online communities whose data they computationally collect and analyze?</h2> <p>As <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2023/06/28/openai-chatgpt-lawsuit-class-action/">OpenAI’s massive scrape of internet data</a> has proven, it’s not only possible but incredibly common for companies, researchers, and regular people to collect users’ personal data without their permission and knowledge. Equally worrisome, it’s just as common for the same parties to lack knowledge about the users whose data they collect.</p> <p>As Bergis Jules, Ed Summers, and Vernon Mitchell put it in <a href="https://www.docnow.io/docs/docnow-whitepaper-2018.pdf">their white paper</a> for Documenting the Now (a project that helps develop tools and practices for ethically archiving social media data):</p> <blockquote> <p>the internet affords the luxury of a certain amount of distance to be able to observe people, consume information generated by and about them, and collect their data without having to participate in equitable engagement as a way to understand their lives, communities, or concerns.</p> </blockquote> <p>For these reasons, they and other scholars argue that <strong>researchers should engage with and be knowledgeable about the communities whom they are studying and collecting data from </strong>— whether through conversation, collaboration, interviews, or ethnographic approaches.</p> <p>By directly engaging with online communities, researchers can make better, more informed, and more context-dependent decisions about other parts of the research process, such as whether to cite a specific user in a published article (more on that below).</p> <p>For example, in Brianna Dym and Casey Fiesler’s <a href="https://journal.transformativeworks.org/index.php/twc/article/view/1733/2445">extremely useful best practices for studying online fandom data</a>, they recommend that researchers who are not familiar with fan communities “spend time [in online fandom spaces] and take the time to talk to fans and to understand and learn their norms,” not only to learn more about the community but also to become more “mindful of each user’s reasonable expectations of privacy, which may be dependent on the community or platform.”</p> <p>They further underscore that making connections with individual users is possible even for large-scale, data-driven research:</p> <blockquote> <p>Even for public data sets in which individual participants might number in the tens of thousands to the millions, it might be possible to talk to some members of the target population in order to better understand what values and concerns people might hold that would deter them from consenting to their data being used.</p> </blockquote> <p>Here are a few concrete examples of this kind of mixed-methods (quantitative/qualitative) approach to studying and engaging with social media communities in action:</p> <ol> <li>In Moya Bailey’s <a href="https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/9/2/000209/000209.html">research on the hashtag #GirlsLikeUs</a>, which was created by trans advocate Janet Mock, Bailey sought Mock’s permission to work on the project before it began, and she collaborated with Mock to develop her research questions and determine the project’s direction. Though Bailey’s research included data collection and quantitative analyses, it was also shaped by a consenting collaborator who was part of the community being studied.</li> <li>In Bailey’s 2020 book with Sarah J. Jackson and Brooke Foucault Welles, <a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262043373/hashtagactivism/"><em>#HashtagActivism: Networks of Race and Gender</em></a>, they similarly frame social media users as collaborators, and they pair each chapter of the book with “an essay written by an influential member of a particular hashtag activism network.”</li> <li>Along similar lines, Deen Freelon, Charlton McIlwain, and Meredith Clark used large-scale network analysis techniques to study 40 million #BlackLivesMatter (BLM) tweets in their report <a href="https://cmsimpact.org/resource/beyond-hashtags-ferguson-blacklivesmatter-online-struggle-offline-justice/">“Beyond the hashtags: #Ferguson, #Blacklivesmatter, and the online struggle for offline justice.”</a> But they also interviewed and talked to dozens of BLM activists and allies “to better understand their thoughts about how social media was and was not useful in their work.”</li> </ol> <h2 id="how-should-researchers-cite-social-media-users-in-published-research">How should researchers cite social media users in published research?</h2> <p>If you want to include or quote a social media post in your published article, <strong>should you</strong> <strong>cite the author, anonymize the author, paraphrase the post, or do something else?</strong> This is another common question that I hear as a social media researcher, and I think it’s an especially important one for humanities scholars, who often include and analyze specific examples of texts in their work (as opposed to computer science researchers, for example, who often work with aggregated representations of data).</p> <p>Before going any further, I want to head off anyone who’s about to spout <strong>the erroneous but distressingly common argument that you can do whatever you want with social media data if it’s “public”</strong> — that is, if it’s published openly on the internet by a public account. Dym and Fieseler (and many other scholars) have <a href="https://journal.transformativeworks.org/index.php/twc/article/view/1733/2445">worked hard</a> to show that this argument is a load of hooey (as my grandma would say). They argue that privacy on the internet is <em>contextual</em>. Your expectation of privacy on Twitter (or X) is going to be very different if you’re a celebrity versus a regular person with 50 followers. And violating those expectations can have serious consequences, as I’ll explain below.</p> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">I helped <a href="https://twitter.com/cfiesler?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@cfiesler</a> make memes for her ethics class and came up with this gem <a href="https://t.co/zGUYPtusaQ">pic.twitter.com/zGUYPtusaQ</a></p>&mdash; Dr. Brianna Dym (@BriannaDym) <a href="https://twitter.com/BriannaDym/status/1220440276579373057?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 23, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <p><em>I showed this meme to my students, and now it lives rent-free in my brain.</em></p> <p>So if you’re including or quoting users’ posts in published scholarship, coming up with a citation strategy is imperative.</p> <p><strong>Many people think that anonymizing social media posts is a good citation strategy that protects users’ privacy. But it’s not.</strong>“Even when anonymized by not including usernames, content from social media collected and shared in research articles can be easily traced back to its creator,” as Dym and Fiesler assert, drawing on a <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41746-018-0036-2">study by John W. Ayers and colleagues</a>. Basically, you can google the text of a social media post and find the original post, context, and its author extremely easily.</p> <p>The other big problem with anonymization is that it robs users of authorship. <strong>Creators deserve intellectual credit</strong> <strong>for what they create and publish</strong>, as <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1023/A:1021316409277">Amy Bruckman and others have maintained</a>.</p> <p>So, anonymizing posts is not a good strategy, and explicitly citing the author of a post is ideal. But citation can be tricky, too. In some cases, it can even be dangerous to cite authors, especially if you do so without their knowledge and permission. Why? <strong>Because citing social media users in a new context can expose them to new and unexpected audiences, which can lead to unwanted attention, harassment, doxxing, personal and professional complications, and other negative outcomes.</strong></p> <p>For example, the Documenting the Now project—which has led social media archiving efforts related to the Ferguson protests, Black Lives Matter, and other social movements—discusses how <a href="https://www.docnow.io/docs/docnow-whitepaper-2018.pdf.">“activists of color . . . face a disproportionate level of harm from surveillance and data collection by law enforcement,”</a> and thus amplifying their words or actions (as documented through social media) might put them in danger, even more so than the average social media user.</p> <p>In a similar vein, when Dym and Fiesler asked LGBTQ fanfiction writers and those with LGBTQ friends in the community how they felt about researchers or journalists citing their stories, they expressed many concerns, including the concern that “exposing fandom content to a broader audience could lead to fans being accidentally outed.”</p> <p>For these reasons, <strong>researchers who wish to cite specific social media posts in published research should make their best effort to contact the authors and seek explicit permission to use the posts.</strong> But there are exceptions. If a user is a public figure, like Joe Biden, or if a post has already reached a wide public audience, like a viral TikTok video, then I personally don’t think that getting direct permission is necessary. However, it can be difficult to draw a line about who counts as a public figure or what counts as reaching a “wide public audience.”</p> <p>In their <a href="https://cmsimpact.org/resource/beyond-hashtags-ferguson-blacklivesmatter-online-struggle-offline-justice/">“Beyond the Hashtags” report</a>, Freelon, McIlwain, and Clark offer a few concrete examples of these <strong>“reasonably public” thresholds</strong> (as I like to think of them). Freelon et al. chose to only cite tweets that met at least one of the following criteria: the tweet had been <strong>retweeted more than 100 times</strong>; the tweet had been published by an <strong>officially verified Twitter account</strong>; and/or the tweet had been published by a <strong>Twitter account with more than 3,000 followers</strong> (placing a user in the top one-percent of the most followed Twitter accounts at that time). Additionally, they did not include the actual text of tweets in their report and <strong>only included links to the tweets</strong>, essentially enabling users to delete their tweets and remove themselves from the study. Devising these kinds of thresholds can be challenging and very subjective, but they can also be helpful for guiding the focus of a study away from obscure content and toward matters of genuine public interest and concern.</p> <p>Frustratingly, Elon Musk’s drastic changes to Twitter have also impacted researchers’ ability to devise some of these thresholds, since he <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2023/04/24/tech/musk-twitter-blue-check-mark/index.html">radically altered X’s “verified” user system</a>. While in the past Twitter would “verify” a user by internally determining that their account was of “public interest” (a process that had its own flaws, to be clear), now this status is exclusively offered to users who pay for an <a href="https://help.twitter.com/en/managing-your-account/about-x-verified-accounts">X Premium monthly subscription</a>. So today, X’s verification system doesn’t tell you anything except who’s paying for X.</p> <p>Sometimes, of course, there are cases when a researcher might want to include a social media post in a publication, but it does not meet these reasonably public thresholds, and its author cannot be reached for comment or to grant permission. What to do then? In these cases, Dym and Fiesler recommend <strong>paraphrasing posts</strong> in such a way that they are not traceable back to the original post or <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/1369118X.2011.641993"><strong>ethically “fabricating” material</strong></a> in ways that Annette Markham has advocated and described, such as by <strong>creating a composite account of a person, interaction, or dialogue</strong>. These strategies may seem foreign and potentially even a little blasphemous to some humanities scholars, especially those who are trained to attend closely to texts and all their nuances. But if these adaptations are necessary to protect users in a given situation, then they obviously need to be embraced. (Basically, lit scholars, we will need to get over ourselves.)</p> <p><strong>What about if you’re studying social media users who you are critical of, such as fascists or white supremacists?</strong> This a question that I did not address in my <em>Debates in the Digital Humanities</em> essay, but I just wanted to raise it briefly here because I think it’s super important. In many ways, I think the best practices I’ve outlined above could still be applied successfully in these cases. If a post is shared by a prominent figure or has reached a wide audience, it’s fair game, and if it doesn’t reach those thresholds, and you can’t get in touch (or don’t want to get in touch) with the author of the post, perhaps you could paraphrase it. (Because of course it could be dangerous to directly contact a fascist or white supremacist and notify them about your involvement in research scrutinizing their behavior and beliefs, and it could be particularly dangerous depending on your identity.) But should you cite the author of such a social media post in full without the author’s permission just because you disagree with them or even disavow them? I’m not sure. Perhaps you could make the case that studying fascist or white supremacist online communities (or whatever communities) is such a matter of public significance that it would justify this choice, that its significance might be akin to a post having reached a wide public audience. But again, I’m not sure. This is an issue that I continue to struggle with, and I would love to hear more about what other people think and what strategies people have developed to address these issues.</p> <h2 id="how-if-at-all-should-researchers-share-users-data">How, if at all, should researchers share users’ data?</h2> <p>While sharing data is a vitally important part of the research process—enabling reproducibility, enhancing evaluation, and increasing accessibility—sharing social media datasets in responsible ways can be very challenging. Social media datasets contain a lot of potentially identifiable information about users, so sharing this kind of data is often explicitly prohibited by platforms’ Terms of Service, and beyond that (because of course we don’t let platforms tell us what’s ethical and what’s not) it’s often considered a privacy violation that can lead to negative consequences for users, such as doxxing, harassment, and other adverse outcomes like those discussed above.</p> <p>One potential strategy for mitigating these harms is to <strong>share social media datasets in ways that enable users’ “right to be forgotten</strong>”—that is, to enable users to remove themselves from the dataset whenever they want. Usually, this means introducing some kind of time lag into the dataset sharing/retrieval process. For example, a researcher might share the code that they used to scrape TikTok posts but not the posts themselves, enabling others to recreate the dataset but not include any posts that have been deleted or removed.</p> <p>Perhaps the best known and most institutionally supported example of this kind of approach was Twitter’s “tweet ID” sharing format—<strong>a format that Elon Musk has virtually destroyed since I published my <em>Debates in DH</em> essay.</strong> A tweet ID is a unique identifier that is associated with every single tweet that’s ever been tweeted. Basically, it’s a unique string of numbers — e.g., <a href="https://twitter.com/icecube/status/1702444061657841919"><em>1702444061657841919</em></a> —that links back to a full, richly embodied tweet, with its text, author, URL, publication date, images/videos, and all its other juicy metadata.</p> <p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*Wt50O_2qjSTW2FixI2cDug.png" alt=""/></p> <p><em><a href="https://archive.org/details/toni-morrison-tweets">A list of tweet ids</a></em></p> <p>Before Musk’s takeover of the platform, you could pass a list of tweet IDs to the Twitter API and download full datasets for the tweets that they referenced—a process known as “hydrating” tweets. The most important part was that you could only download data for tweets that still existed. Because a tweet ID will only link back to a tweet if it has not been deleted or if its account has not been made private or suspended, etc. For these reasons, Ed Summers, the technical lead of the Documenting the Now project, has suggested that <a href="https://medium.com/on-archivy/on-forgetting-e01a2b95272">tweet IDs advance an implicit ethical position</a> by allowing users “to exercise their right to be forgotten.” By deleting a tweet or making their account private, users can remove themselves from all future versions of the data.</p> <p>Twitter’s policies have long forbidden people from publicly sharing full datasets of tweets, but it has allowed people to openly share tweet IDs. And until recently (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20231118053057/https://developer.twitter.com/en/developer-terms/policy#4-e">as recently as November 18, 2023</a>), academics were even explicitly permitted to share as many tweet IDs as they wanted:</p> <blockquote> <p><em>If you provide Twitter Content to third parties, including downloadable datasets or via an API</em><strong><em>, you may only distribute Tweet IDs, Direct Message IDs, and/or User IDs</em></strong> <em>(except as described below).</em> <strong><em>We also grant special permissions to academic researchers sharing Tweet IDs and User IDs for non-commercial research purposes.</em></strong></p> </blockquote> <blockquote> <p><em>In total, you may not distribute more than 1,500,000 Tweet IDs to any entity…within any 30 day period unless you have received written permission from Twitter…</em><strong><em>Academic researchers are permitted to distribute an unlimited number of Tweet IDs</em></strong> <em>and/or User IDs if they are doing so on behalf of an academic institution and for the sole purpose of non-commercial research.</em></p> </blockquote> <p>Because of this institutional support and its inherent “right to be forgotten” capacities, many researchers chose to share their data as tweet IDs in the last decade or so. The DocNow project even created a <a href="https://catalog.docnow.io/">catalog of tweet IDs</a>, which now hosts more than 7 billion of them—linking back to full Twitter datasets about COVID, Donald Trump, Toni Morrison, natural disasters, celebrities, protest movements, the alt-right, and many other important subjects. Summers also created a widely-used GUI application called <a href="https://github.com/DocNow/hydrator">“Hydrator,”</a> which conveniently allowed people to download tweets from lists of tweet IDs via the API but without ever touching the command line or writing a single line of code.</p> <p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*JFZVbhfp_8GBKto9asYozw.png" alt=""/></p> <p><em>DocNow Catalog (<a href="https://catalog.docnow.io/">https://catalog.docnow.io/</a>)</em></p> <p>But today, sadly, Musk’s dismantling of the API and other radical policy changes have robbed DocNow’s incredible Catalog and Hydrator app and even their <a href="https://twarc-project.readthedocs.io/en/latest/">Twitter collection tool twarc</a> of much of their usefulness. (The DocNow team has written about <a href="https://medium.com/documenting-docnow/looking-forwards-64cee8436640">the demise of these tools here</a>, offering their own perspective on paths forward.) Because today, with the current <a href="https://developer.twitter.com/en/docs/twitter-api/getting-started/about-twitter-api#item0">“Free” tier of the Twitter API</a>, you can’t hydrate any tweet IDs at all. And with the <a href="https://developer.twitter.com/en/docs/twitter-api/getting-started/about-twitter-api#item0">$100-a-month “Basic” tier</a> and the <a href="https://developer.twitter.com/en/docs/twitter-api/getting-started/about-twitter-api#item0">$5,000-a-month “Pro” tier</a>, you can only retrieve (“pull”) 10,000 tweets and 1 million tweets per month, respectively. This is a severe curtailing of what used to be possible. Seven years ago, when I was a graduate student, I was able to hydrate 30 million tweets in under a week with only free access to the Twitter API. The <a href="https://dfreelon.org/2017/01/03/beyond-the-hashtags-twitter-data/">tweet IDs that I hydrated</a> were publicly shared by Freelon, McIlwain, and Clark from their “Beyond the Hashtags” report, and their generous data sharing was what made it possible for me to do the research that would become my first published article. I didn’t have the funding or capacity at the time to get this data in any other way. And it’s sad to me that today’s graduate students, as well as other researchers with limited funding, will not be able to benefit from the same kind of data sharing.</p> <p>In addition to the severe curtailing of the API, X also recently (again very recently, since November 18, 2023) <a href="https://developer.twitter.com/en/developer-terms/policy#4-e">changed its developer policy</a> with regard to tweet IDs (which they now call “post IDs”). Academics are no longer permitted to share as many post IDs as they want, and in fact there are new clauses that suggest that, before sharing post IDs, X <a href="https://developer.twitter.com/en/developer-terms/policy#4-e">must explicitly approve of the research related to the post IDs in writing</a> (unclear if this approval includes having previously been approved for a Academic Twitter API account):</p> <blockquote> <p><em>If you provide</em> <strong><em>X Content</em></strong> <em>to third parties, including downloadable datasets or via an API, you may only distribute</em> <strong><em>Post IDs</em></strong><em>, Direct Message IDs, and/or User IDs (except as described below).</em></p> </blockquote> <blockquote> <p><em>In total, you may not distribute more than 1,500,000 Post IDs to any entity…within any 30 day period unless you have received written permission from X….Academic researchers are permitted to distribute Post IDs and/or User IDs solely for the purposes of non-commercial research on behalf of an academic institution, and</em> <strong><em>that has been approved by X in writing, or peer review or validation of such research. Only as many Post IDs or User IDs that is necessary for such research, and has been approved by X may be used.</em></strong></p> </blockquote> <p>So what will become of the billions of tweet IDs shared by researchers that are now basically inaccessible through the API? And how else can we responsibly share Twitter data — or other kinds of social media data?</p> <p>Another strategy for sharing social media datasets is <strong>to use institutional repositories like the new</strong> <a href="https://socialmediaarchive.org/pages/?page=About&amp;ln=en"><strong>Social Media Archive</strong></a> <strong>(SOMAR)</strong>, housed by the <a href="https://www.icpsr.umich.edu/">Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research</a> (ICPSR) at the University of Michigan. SOMAR is promising because it allows researchers to place restrictions on the datasets that they share, so it’s possible to deposit and share a social media dataset but require anybody who wishes to access the data <a href="https://somar.infoready4.com/#">to submit an application that might include</a>: proof of affiliation with an academic institution and a terminal degree, a summary of the research that they intend to do, proof of IRB approval from their own institution, a signed restricted data agreement, and more. Additionally, when depositing data into SOMAR, researchers can choose to restrict access to a <a href="https://socialmediaarchive.org/pages/?page=FAQs&amp;ln=en">Virtual Data Enclave (VDE)</a>, so that others can’t actually download the data or take the data anywhere beyond the platform. (It’s also possible to make data publicly available for direct download, or to make data available for direct download with only a login to a SOMAR account.) So perhaps researchers who previously shared their Twitter data as tweet IDs on the DocNow Catalog might instead deposit their Twitter datasets into SOMAR with appropriate restrictions.</p> <p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*hbx30I_VxGt8kpg_gyn8rw.png" alt=""/></p> <p><em>SOMAR (<a href="https://socialmediaarchive.org/">https://socialmediaarchive.org/</a>)</em></p> <p>Interestingly, SOMAR is also supported by <a href="https://www.icpsr.umich.edu/web/about/cms/4081">a $1.3 million gift from Meta</a>, and Meta has just unveiled a <a href="https://transparency.fb.com/researchtools/meta-content-library">new academic research API</a> that is exclusively available through SOMAR’s Virtual Data Enclave (VDE). They also announced that ICPSR and SOMAR will <a href="https://www.icpsr.umich.edu/web/about/cms/5231">handle all of the applications</a> for research access to Meta’s new API. This partnership introduces a new model for academic social media research, attempting to close the gap between Big Tech social media and the academy, and eliminating the need to share data by never letting the data leave in the first place. The fact that Meta has so much unilateral power in determining what data researchers can access through this API/platform—as well as what researchers can do with that data—is concerning. When Meta has provided data to researchers in the past and asked researchers to trust them without transparency, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/live/2020/2020-election-misinformation-distortions#facebook-sent-flawed-data-to-misinformation-researchers">it has <em>not</em> worked out well</a>. But who knows what will happen with this new partnership.</p> <p>Despite these concerns, I am still interested in and curious about SOMAR’s future. The repository addresses a pressing need in the field that is not being addressed in very many other places. Of course, there are additional drawbacks to sharing data in repositories like SOMAR. For example, some of the restrictions that can be placed on data are exclusionary to those who are not academic researchers with terminal degrees, likely making some data unavailable to the communities who actually created it. (Enabling communities to access and control their own data has long been a goal of the DocNow project, and they recently wrote about the benefits of diversifying <a href="https://medium.com/documenting-docnow/looking-forwards-64cee8436640">“who can use web and social media archiving tools to create data collections…beyond academic researchers and the handful of archivists at academic and national libraries”</a>). Also, these kinds of dataset deposits do not inherently enable users’ right to be forgotten as some other data sharing approaches do. But for now, it is still better than most alternatives (like openly publishing sensitive user data or allowing valuable archives of social movements to die on old computers), so I think it’s worth paying attention to.</p> <hr/> <p>The world of social media changes rapidly, as the last year has shown us. (I mean, for real, providing updates on all of Elon Musk’s antics has made this update almost as long as my original essay.) To keep pace, the conversation about working with social media data will need to change and evolve, too. But I think the model demonstrated by the researchers discussed above—which emphasizes actual engagement and conversation with social media users, explicit permission with regard to quotation and citation of posts, responsible data sharing practices, and a prioritization of the most vulnerable—can provide a solid foundation for the future. And in that future, I think that researchers will need to be sure to develop social media data infrastructures and approaches that are distinct from, and even explicitly opposed to Big Tech platforms, even as we find ourselves sometimes necessarily collaborating with them.</p> <p><strong>Footnotes</strong></p> <p>1: Some professional academic organizations, like the <a href="https://aoir.org/">Association of Internet Researchers</a> (AoIR), have published guidelines for working with internet data: <a href="https://aoir.org/ethics/">https://aoir.org/ethics/</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="data-viz"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://melaniewalsh.org/%7B%22thumb%22=%3E%22../images/banner-purple.png%22%7D"/><media:content medium="image" url="https://melaniewalsh.org/%7B%22thumb%22=%3E%22../images/banner-purple.png%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"/></entry><entry><title type="html">Introducing an Interactive Textbook for Cultural Analysis with Python</title><link href="https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2021/intro-ca-jupyter-book/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introducing an Interactive Textbook for Cultural Analysis with Python"/><published>2021-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2021/intro-ca-jupyter-book</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2021/intro-ca-jupyter-book/"><![CDATA[<meta property="twitter:image" content="../../../assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/intro-ca-home-page-12-30-2020.png"/> <p>In this blog post, I will give a brief overview of my work-in-progress textbook, <a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/"><em>Introduction to Cultural Analytics &amp; Python</em>,</a> which I made with a stellar new project called <a href="https://jupyterbook.org/intro.html">Jupyter Book</a>. Thanks to Jupyter Book, the textbook includes interactive code, responsive data visualizations, downloadable Jupyter notebooks, and a lot of other neat features.</p> <p class="notice--purple"> <b>What is a Jupyter notebook?</b> <br/> <a href="https://jupyter-notebook-beginner-guide.readthedocs.io/en/latest/what_is_jupyter.html#notebook-document">Jupyter notebooks</a> are special documents that can combine runnable programming code with regular text, images, links, and a lot more. Jupyter notebooks are very useful for exploring, teaching, and learning code. </p> <p>I developed this textbook for an undergraduate course that I’m teaching at Cornell, <a href="https://classes.cornell.edu/browse/roster/SP21/class/INFO/1350">“Introduction to Cultural Analytics: Data, Computation, &amp; Culture,”</a> which introduces Python programming to students who are interested in the humanities and social sciences. Most of the students have no previous background or training in programming.</p> <p><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/"><img src="../../../assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/intro-ca-home-page-12-30-2020.png" alt="Intro Cultural Analytics home page"/></a></p> <p>Throughout the semester, we text mine <a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Text-Analysis/TF-IDF-HathiTrust.html">short stories</a>, <a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Data-Collection/Song-Lyrics-Analysis.html#word-count-data-viz-with-pandas">songs</a>, and <a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Data-Collection/Twitter-Data-Analysis.html#display-links-and-images-in-twitter-data">tweets</a>. We analyze character networks from <a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Network-Analysis/Network-Analysis.html#calculate-degree"><em>Game of Thrones</em></a> and study <a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Data-Analysis/Pandas-Basics-Part3.html">dialogue from Hollywood films</a>. We also reflect about the complexities of reducing human life to data and try to develop methodologies geared toward justice. We engage with historical data about <a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Data-Analysis/Pandas-Basics-Part1.html">Irish immigrants</a> and <a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Data-Analysis/Pandas-Basics-Part2.html">enslaved people from the Trans-Atlantic Slave Trade</a>, as well as scholars’ prior data-driven work in these areas. We discuss <a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Data-Collection/User-Ethics-Legal-Concerns.html">ethical challenges</a> related to social media data collection, and we explore the <a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Mapping/Mapping.html#torn-apart-separados">data</a> behind projects like <a href="http://xpmethod.columbia.edu/torn-apart/volume/1/">Torn Apart/Separados</a>, which maps the locations of Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE) detention facilities.</p> <p>I’m including a quick outline of the material you can find in my textbook below. After this outline, I discuss why I used Jupyter Book to make the textbook, and why I think Jupyter Book is a game-changer for publications and educational resources that involve code. In short, you can publish a collection of Jupyter notebooks as a good-looking, easily navigable online book, where users can hide and reveal content, explore interactive data visualizations, open and run code in the cloud via Binder or Google CoLab, and a lot more.</p> <h1 id="introduction-to-cultural-analytics--python"><em>Introduction to Cultural Analytics &amp; Python</em></h1> <p>Here’s a snapshot of some of the material and lessons you can find in <a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/"><em>Introduction to Cultural Analytics &amp; Python</em></a>:</p> <ul> <li><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/course-schedule.html">Course readings and schedule for “Introduction to Cultural Analytics,” undergraduate course taught at Cornell University in Spring 2020 and 2021</a></li> <li><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Datasets/Datasets.html">Datasets related to humanities and culture</a> <a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Datasets/Datasets.html"><img src="../../../assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/datasets-zoom.png" alt=""/></a></li> <li> <p><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Command-Line/The-Command-Line.html">Introduction to the command line</a> <a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Command-Line/The-Command-Line.html"><img src="../../../assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/command-line-zoom.png" alt=""/></a></p> </li> <li>Python basics <ul> <li><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Python/Variables.html">Variables</a></li> <li><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Python/Data-Types.html">Data types</a></li> <li><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Python/String-Methods.html">String methods</a> <a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Python/String-Methods.html"><img src="../../../assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/string-methods.png" alt=""/></a></li> <li><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Python/Comparisons-Conditionals.html">Comparisons and conditionals</a></li> <li><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Python/Lists-Loops-Part1.html">Lists and loops</a></li> <li><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Python/Dictionaries.html">Dictionaries</a></li> <li><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Python/Dictionaries.html">Functions</a></li> </ul> </li> <li>Data analysis with Pandas <ul> <li><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Data-Analysis/Pandas-Basics-Part1.html">Historical data about Irish immigrants</a> <a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Data-Analysis/Pandas-Basics-Part1.html"><img src="../../../assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/almshouse.png" alt=""/></a></li> <li><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Data-Analysis/Pandas-Basics-Part2.html">Historical data about the Trans-Atlantic Slave Trade</a></li> <li><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Data-Analysis/Pandas-Basics-Part3.html">Data about Hollywood movie dialogue</a></li> </ul> </li> <li>Data collection <ul> <li><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Data-Collection/User-Ethics-Legal-Concerns.html">Best practices for social media data collection</a></li> <li><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Data-Collection/Web-Scraping-Part1.html">Web scraping Genius.com with BeautifulSoup &amp; LyricsGenius</a> <a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Data-Collection/Web-Scraping-Part2.html"><img src="../../../assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/song-lyrics-zoom.png" alt=""/></a></li> <li><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Data-Collection/Twitter-Data-Collection.html">Collecting tweets with Twitter API &amp; Twarc</a></li> <li><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Data-Collection/Reddit-Data-Collection-With-PSAW.html">Collecting Reddit posts with Pushshift</a></li> </ul> </li> <li>Text analysis <ul> <li>Term Frequency-Inverse Document Frequency <ul> <li><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Text-Analysis/TF-IDF-HathiTrust.html">With in-copyright book data from the HathiTrust Digital Library</a> <a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Text-Analysis/TF-IDF-Scikit-Learn.html"><img src="../../../assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/tf-idf-hathi-trust.png" alt=""/></a></li> <li><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Text-Analysis/TF-IDF-Scikit-Learn.html">With plain text files</a></li> </ul> </li> <li>Topic Modeling with Little MALLET Wrapper <ul> <li><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Text-Analysis/Topic-Modeling-Text-Files.html"><em>New York Times</em> obituaries</a></li> <li><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Text-Analysis/Topic-Modeling-CSV.html">Am I The Asshole? Reddit posts</a></li> <li><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Text-Analysis/Topic-Modeling-Time-Series.html">Donald Trump tweets</a> <a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Text-Analysis/Topic-Modeling-Time-Series.html"><img src="../../../assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/topic-model-time.png" alt=""/></a></li> </ul> </li> <li><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Text-Analysis/Named-Entity-Recognition.html">Named Entity Recognition with spaCy</a></li> <li><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Text-Analysis/POS-Keywords.html">Part-of-speech tagging with spaCy</a></li> </ul> </li> <li>Network analysis <ul> <li><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Network-Analysis/Network-Analysis.html">With NetworkX and <em>Game of Thrones</em> characters</a> <a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Network-Analysis/Network-Analysis.html"><img src="../../../assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/networks.png" alt=""/></a></li> <li><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Network-Analysis/Making-Network-Viz-with-Bokeh.html">Making interactive networks with Bokeh</a></li> </ul> </li> <li>Mapping <ul> <li><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Mapping/Mapping.html#geocoding-with-geopy">Geocoding</a></li> <li><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Mapping/Mapping.html#making-interactive-maps">Making interactive maps with Folium</a> <a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Mapping/Mapping.html#making-interactive-maps"><img src="../../../assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/map.png" alt=""/></a></li> <li><a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/Mapping/Publish-Your-Map.html">Publishing maps on the web</a></li> </ul> </li> <li>Future content <ul> <li>In the future, I plan to add sections on object-oriented programming, virtual environments, git, and VSCode</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <h1 id="why-jupyter-book-what-is-jupyter-book">Why Jupyter Book? What is Jupyter Book?</h1> <p>My undergraduate class, “Introduction to Cultural Analytics,” falls into a research area known as digital humanities or cultural analytics (as the title suggests), which blends digital and computational methods with humanities and culture. This academic field has been growing rapidly over the last 20 years, so luckily I had a lot of great, already existing resources to draw from when developing my class — such as Python-based course materials from <a href="https://github.com/laurenfklein/emory-qtm340">Lauren Klein</a>, <a href="https://mimno.infosci.cornell.edu/info3350/">David Mimno</a>, and <a href="https://github.com/aparrish/rwet">Allison Parrish</a>.</p> <p>These course materials are awesome for many reasons, but one especially awesome thing is that they include the actual Python code taught in classes. Publishing this code online allows students to reference and return to the material covered in class, but it also allows people who are not enrolled in the class — instructors, students, or people who are just plain interested — to learn and follow along, too. There’s a big appetite for learning these computational skills, especially among people from humanities disciplines who have minimal or non-traditional programming education and experience. So these materials are an important resource for the whole community.</p> <p>Most of this code is published as Jupyter notebooks — special documents that can combine runnable programming code with regular text, images, links, and a lot more. Jupyter notebooks are very useful for exploring, teaching, and learning code.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/functions-jb-notebook.png" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/functions-jb-notebook.png" width="100%" height="auto" alt="Example of a Jupyter notebook about Python functions and Beyonce" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">*Example of a Jupyter notebook about Python functions and Beyonce*</figcaption> </figure> <p>I <em>love</em> Jupyter notebooks. I use them all the time. But I also recognize that Jupyter notebooks can be challenging to work with and can seem confusing if you’re not familiar with them. For example, you can’t open a Jupyter notebook — or run its code — unless you have the right software installed <em>and</em> running on your own computer.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/jb-notebook-cant-open.png" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/jb-notebook-cant-open.png" width="100%" height="auto" alt="Jupyter notebooks can be confusing to open" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">*Jupyter notebooks can be confusing to open and use*</figcaption> </figure> <p>Recognizing this problem, GitHub, a popular repository for hosting code, allows you to preview static versions of Jupyter notebooks on the web, even if you don’t have the right software installed and running. This is an awesome feature!</p> <p>But these GitHub previews are often slow to load, and they don’t always look exactly the way you want. What’s more, if you’re not familiar with it, GitHub can be pretty confusing, too. I found GitHub to be a very non-intuitive and intimidating platform to navigate at first.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/github-something-went-wrong.png" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/github-something-went-wrong.png" width="100%" height="auto" alt="Jupyter notebooks don't always load well on GitHub" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">*Jupyter notebooks don't always load well on GitHub*</figcaption> </figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/github-output-scroll.gif" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/github-output-scroll.gif" width="100%" height="auto" alt="Jupyter notebooks don't always load well on GitHub" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">*Long outputs can be cumbersome on GitHub*</figcaption> </figure> <p>This is all to say that publishing code-based course materials on GitHub is mostly great, especially if you introduce your students to GitHub or they’re already familiar with it.</p> <p>But for my course materials, I hoped to have a little more control over aesthetics, navigation, and display, and I hoped to reach an audience of people who might not be familiar with GitHub yet. So I started researching alternatives. That’s when I found the incredible, newly launched <a href="https://jupyterbook.org/intro.html">Jupyter Book project</a>. The Jupyter Book resource can transform a collection of Jupyter notebooks into nicely readable, aesthetically pleasing HTML files and publish them as an easily navigable online book. All you need is the command-line tool and a directory of Jupyter notebooks organized in the right way with a special configuration file and table of contents.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/functions-jb-page-updated.png" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/functions-jb-page-updated.png" width="100%" height="auto" alt="Python functions Jupyter notebook published as a page in *Introduction to Cultural Analytics &amp; Python*" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">*Python functions Jupyter notebook published as a page in Introduction to Cultural Analytics &amp; Python*</figcaption> </figure> <p>But making pretty web pages is not all Jupyter Book can do. When you’re reading through a page in an online Jupyter Book, you can also download a PDF of that page or the actual Jupyter notebook file behind the page, which means that you can open it and run the code on your own computer. You can also open up that same Jupyter notebook in the cloud — via Binder or Google CoLab — and play with the code without configuring any software or dependencies. Can you tell that I find all this exciting?</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/functions-updated-speedy.gif" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/functions-updated-speedy.gif" width="100%" height="auto" alt="Download PDFs, .ipynb files, or open and play with code in the cloud" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">*Download PDFs, .ipynb files, or open and play with code in the cloud*</figcaption> </figure> <p>I found the Jupyter Book project so exciting that I decided to bundle up my course materials and publish them as a Jupyter Book.</p> <p>The textbook is still being updated and revised, but so far it’s proved to be a useful resource for my students. Because I published all the Jupyter notebooks that we covered in class, my students could easily reference and review materials after class, but they could also use it during class. If some software package wasn’t working on a particular student’s computer — an occurrence that seems frankly unavoidable even with the best preparation and troubleshooting from instructors and TAs — they could just open up the Jupyter notebook for that day’s class in the cloud via Binder and work through the code remotely. This gave us a chance to resolve specific technical issues later and helped keep students from falling behind during class.</p> <p>Beyond its interactive code capabilities, Jupyter Book has loads of other cool features. You can create <a href="https://jupyterbook.org/content/content-blocks.html">attention-grabbing content blocks</a> for notes, warnings, and tips — or for anything else you want. They’re customizable!</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/installation-zoom.png" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/installation-zoom.png" width="100%" height="auto" alt="Note content block" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">*Note content block*</figcaption> </figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/pandas-review-zoom.png" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/pandas-review-zoom.png" width="100%" height="auto" alt="Custom content block from *Introduction to Cultural Analytics &amp; Python*, featuring cute panda emoji" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">*Custom content block featuring cute panda emoji*</figcaption> </figure> <p>You can <a href="https://jupyterbook.org/interactive/hiding.html">hide code cells</a> and allow users to reveal them.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/list-comprehensions2.gif" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/list-comprehensions2.gif" width="100%" height="auto" alt="Using the click-to-show feature in *Introduction to Cultural Analytics &amp; Python*, featuring list comprehensions" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">*Click-to-show code featuring list comprehensions*</figcaption> </figure> <p>You can <a href="https://jupyterbook.org/content/code-outputs.html?highlight=output%20scroll#scrolling-cell-outputs">enable scrolling</a> for really long outputs.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/ner-output-scroll.gif" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/ner-output-scroll.gif" width="100%" height="auto" alt="Using output scrolling feature in *Introduction to Cultural Analytics &amp; Python*, featuring spaCy NER of Ada Lovelace's obituary" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">*Output scrolling featuring spaCy Named Entity Recognition of Ada Lovelace's obituary*</figcaption> </figure> <p>You can even publish <a href="https://jupyterbook.org/interactive/interactive.html">interactive data visualizations</a>.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/network-updated.gif" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/network-updated.gif" width="100%" height="auto" alt="Interactive data visualizations featuring Game of Thrones characters" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">*Interactive data visualizations featuring Game of Thrones characters*</figcaption> </figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/map-interactive.gif" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/map-interactive.gif" width="100%" height="auto" alt="Interactive data visualizations featuring a map of Ithaca, NY" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">*Interactive data visualizations featuring a map of Ithaca, NY*</figcaption> </figure> <p>There are tons of other awesome Jupyter Book features not covered here, and many more still being developed. The Jupyter Book community is super active and responsive. They regularly roll out new versions and <a href="https://github.com/executablebooks/jupyter-book/issues">eagerly engage with users</a>. Over the last year, Jupyter Book developers like Chris Holdgraf and Chris Sewell have patiently helped me troubleshoot issues, listened to my suggestions, and even helped promote my textbook! It’s been a genuine pleasure to interact with them and the rest of the community.</p> <p>I’m very excited about the future of Jupyter Book, and I think that digital humanities/cultural analytics scholars can really benefit from and contribute to it.</p> <h1 id="want-to-build-your-own-jupyter-book">Want to Build Your Own Jupyter Book?</h1> <p>You can find all the code for <em>Introduction to Cultural Analytics &amp; Python</em> <a href="https://github.com/melaniewalsh/Intro-Cultural-Analytics">in this GitHub repository</a>. In the README, I briefly explain the structure of the repository and what’s required to generate a Jupyter Book. You can also learn more by reading the Jupyter Book <a href="https://jupyterbook.org/intro.html">documentation</a> and by exploring <a href="https://executablebooks.org/en/latest/gallery.html">the Jupyter Books and repositories in the featured gallery</a>.</p> <h1 id="feedback">Feedback?</h1> <p>If you have feedback or suggestions about <em>Introduction to Cultural Analytics &amp; Python</em>, or you happen to find it useful, please let me know! I’d love to hear from you via email, <a href="https://twitter.com/mellymeldubs">Twitter</a>, or <a href="https://github.com/melaniewalsh/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/issues">GitHub</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jupyter-book"/><category term="text-analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A brief overview of my work-in-progress textbook, and why I made it with the awesome new resource Jupyter Book]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://melaniewalsh.org/assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/intro-ca-home-page-12-30-2020.png%22%7D"/><media:content medium="image" url="https://melaniewalsh.org/assets/img/intro-ca-blog-images/intro-ca-home-page-12-30-2020.png%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"/></entry><entry><title type="html">A Million Tweeted Tributes to Toni Morrison</title><link href="https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2019/toni-morrison-tweeted-tributes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Million Tweeted Tributes to Toni Morrison"/><published>2019-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2019/toni-morrison-tweeted-tributes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2019/toni-morrison-tweeted-tributes/"><![CDATA[<p>Toni Morrison, one of the best and most influential literary writers of the 20th and 21st centuries, died on Monday. She was the first Black woman to win the Nobel Prize in literature and the author of eleven novels, dozens of essays, as well as literary criticism. When Morrison’s publisher announced the news of her death on Tuesday morning, thousands of people began mourning her incredible life on Twitter. Within a little over a day, more than 500,000 Twitter users in fact cited Toni Morrison specifically by first and last name in a million tweets and retweets.</p> <p>To preserve this powerful commemoration of a historic American author, I started collecting tweets that mentioned “Toni Morrison” with <a href="https://github.com/DocNow/twarc">twarc</a>, a digital tool created by Ed Summers and <a href="https://www.docnow.io/">DocNow</a>. At the end of this blog post, I explain how you can access the <a href="https://archive.org/details/toni-morrison-tweets">tweets from this archive</a>—only if the tweets are still public and have not been deleted by their creator—and I outline some ethical considerations and best practices if you plan to use this data.</p> <p>But first I wanted to share a quick overview of the roughly one million tweets and retweets that paid tribute to Toni Morrison’s life in the day after the news broke.</p> <p><strong>Total Duration of this Snapshot:</strong> 1 day, 3 hours<br/> <strong>Earliest Tweet:</strong> 9:08AM (CST) August 6, 2019 <br/> <strong>Latest Tweet:</strong> 12:18PM (CST) August 7, 2019</p> <p><strong>Number of Tweets That Mentioned Toni Morrison:</strong> 976,014<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> <br/> <strong>Number of Twitter Users:</strong> 510,093 <br/> <strong>Number of Languages Used in Tweets:</strong> 48</p> <h1 id="top-10-most-retweeted">Top 10 Most Retweeted</h1> <ol> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Toni Morrison was a national treasure, as good a storyteller, as captivating, in person as she was on the page. Her writing was a beautiful, meaningful challenge to our conscience and our moral imagination. What a gift to breathe the same air as her, if only for a while. <a href="https://t.co/JG7Jgu4p9t">pic.twitter.com/JG7Jgu4p9t</a></p>&mdash; Barack Obama (@BarackObama) <a href="https://twitter.com/BarackObama/status/1158764847800213507?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">August 6, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <p>Former President Barack Obama’s celebration of Morrison was the most widely recirculated tweet in the wake of her death, and it was shared over 50,000 times. The photo that he included of himself and Morrison was taken in 2012 on the day that she received the Presidential Medal of Freedom, the highest civilian award in the U.S.</p> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">One of my favorite interviews with Toni Morrison. The interviewer asked her when she was going to “substantially” write about white people. Her response? “You can’t understand how powerfully racist that question is, can you?” <a href="https://t.co/WFhNMgx7xv">pic.twitter.com/WFhNMgx7xv</a></p>&mdash; Paul McCallion (@OrangePaulp) <a href="https://twitter.com/OrangePaulp/status/1158752990876110850?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">August 6, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <p>This video clip, in which Morrison confronts Australian journalist Jana Wendt for asking a “powerfully racist” question during their 1998 interview, was retweeted more than 50,000 times, and it was shared in many other tweets, as well. Quotations and video clips from Morrison’s media appearances were extensively featured in tweets memorializing the author’s life and career.</p> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Toni Morrison: 40<br/>Mark Twain: 41<br/>Marcel Proust: 43<br/>Henry Miller: 44<br/>JRR Tolkien: 45<br/>Raymond Chandler: 51<br/>Richard Adams: 52<br/>Annie Proulx: 57<br/>Laura Ingalls Wilder: 65<br/>Frank McCourt: 66<br/>Harriett Doerr: 74<br/>Harry Bernstein: 96<br/>No, you’re not too old to publish your first book.</p>&mdash; Allison K Williams (@GuerillaMemoir) <a href="https://twitter.com/GuerillaMemoir/status/1031295024984743937?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">August 19, 2018</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <p>Many tweets in the wake of Morrison’s death reflected on the age at which she published her first novel, <em>The Bluest Eye</em> (1970), 40 years old. This particular tweet was first shared almost a year earlier and gained renewed momentum after Morrison’s passing.</p> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;If you can only be tall because somebody is on their knees, then you have a serious problem. And my feeling is white people have a very, very serious problem, and they should start thinking about what they can do about it.” <br/><br/>Rest In Power Toni Morrison<a href="https://t.co/KD0mukv4x0">pic.twitter.com/KD0mukv4x0</a></p>&mdash; Keith Boykin (@keithboykin) <a href="https://twitter.com/keithboykin/status/1158737452493934592?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">August 6, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <p>Another remediated television interview, a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CGeNJewyo4o">1993 conversation</a> between Morrison and Charlie Rose, also became a popular source for Twitter users venerating Toni Morrison. Many users particularly latched onto her claim during this interview that “[i]f you can only be tall because someone else is on their knees, then you have a serious problem.”</p> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">“He licked his lips. ‘Well, if you want my opinion-‘<br/>‘I don’t, ‘ She said. ‘I have my own.”<br/>— Toni Morrison, BELOVED</p>&mdash; Saeed Jones (@theferocity) <a href="https://twitter.com/theferocity/status/1158733930658455554?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">August 6, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <p>This excerpt from Morrison’s Pulitzer-Prize-winning novel <em>Beloved</em> (1997) comes from an exchange between Paul D. and Denver near the end of the narrative. It is notable that this quotation is taken from a work of Morrison’s fiction—with the trappings of third-person narration and dialogue—since the other most retweeted quotations were cribbed from nonfictional television interviews.</p> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">“If you can only be tall because someone else is on their knees, then you have a serious problem. And white people have a very very serious problem” - Toni Morrison <br/><br/> <a href="https://t.co/3MTn8MoelG">pic.twitter.com/3MTn8MoelG</a></p>&mdash; George M Johnson (@IamGMJohnson) <a href="https://twitter.com/IamGMJohnson/status/1158750398196408320?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">August 6, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">The best way to honour Toni Morrison is to continue her legacy by celebrating and supporting Black female writers. So here’s a thread of fantastic women whose work you should read.</p>&mdash; Sister Outrider (@ClaireShrugged) <a href="https://twitter.com/ClaireShrugged/status/1158780575202852864?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">August 6, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <p>A significant number of the tweets in this archive, such as the one featured above, praised Morrison as a central node in a literary network of Black women writers. This tweet made the network explicit as well as expanded it by tagging the Twitter user names of dozens of Black women authors in a 20-plus-part thread.</p> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">“if you can only be tall because somebody’s on their knees, you have a serious problem.” - toni morrison <a href="https://t.co/MEIt2iEynH">pic.twitter.com/MEIt2iEynH</a></p>&mdash; nadirah (@hinadirah) <a href="https://twitter.com/hinadirah/status/1158733669923770368?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">August 6, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Toni Morrison’s knife is so sharp, you don’t even realize that she’s slit your throat. <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ToniMorrison?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#ToniMorrison</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/WhenIGrowUp?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#WhenIGrowUp</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/IAmTheMainstream?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#IAmTheMainstream</a> <a href="https://t.co/6C7PJOqzrv">pic.twitter.com/6C7PJOqzrv</a></p>&mdash; Stony Morrison, PhD (@rrandolphjr) <a href="https://twitter.com/rrandolphjr/status/1095007929898545153?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">February 11, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <p>Like the #2 most retweeted Toni Morrison citation, the above tweet also included a video clip from Morrison’s 1998 interview with Jana Wendt. Like #3, it was also a tweet first published months earlier, back in February 2019. This pattern makes clear that some Toni Morrison tweets and videos had long circulating lives on the internet and that they took on renewed significance in the wake of Morrison’s death.</p> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Toni Morrison published her first novel at 40 years-old. You have time. We have time.</p>&mdash; Asia 🌱 (@AsiaChloeBrown) <a href="https://twitter.com/AsiaChloeBrown/status/1158759741155422213?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">August 6, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> </ol> <h1 id="top-quotations-in-tweets">Top Quotations in Tweets</h1> <ol> <li> <blockquote> <p>“If you can only be tall because somebody is on their knees, then you have a serious problem. And my feeling is: White people have a very, very serious problem, and they should start thinking about what they can do about it.”</p> </blockquote> <p>Excerpted from a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CGeNJewyo4o">Charlie Rose interview</a> (1993)</p> </li> <li> <blockquote> <p>“I tell my students, ‘When you get these jobs that you have been so brilliantly trained for, just remember that your real job is that if you are free, you need to free somebody else. If you have some power, then your job is to empower somebody else.’”</p> </blockquote> <p>Excerpted from an <a href="https://www.oprah.com/omagazine/toni-morrison-talks-love/all"><em>Oprah Magazine</em> interview</a> (2003)</p> </li> <li> <blockquote> <p>“We die. That may be the meaning of life. But we do language. That may be the measure of our lives.”</p> </blockquote> <p>Excerpted from Morrison’s <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ticXzFEpN9o">Nobel Lecture</a> (1993)</p> </li> <li> <blockquote> <p>“‘Well, if you want my opinion—’<br/> ‘I don’t,’ She said. ‘I have my own.’”</p> </blockquote> <p>Excerpted from <em>Beloved</em> (1987)</p> </li> <li> <blockquote> <p>“If there is a book that you want to read but it hasn’t been written yet, you must be the one to write it.”</p> </blockquote> <p>Excerpted from <a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2018/07/16/unwritten/">a 1981 speech at the Ohio Arts Council</a> later reported on by <em>The Cincinnati Enquirer</em></p> </li> <li> <blockquote> <p>“Love is or it ain’t. Thin love ain’t love at all.”</p> </blockquote> <p>Excerpted from <em>Beloved</em> (1987)</p> </li> </ol> <p>You can also see a <a href="../../../assets/img/morrison/common_quotations_toni_morrison_tweets.png">bar chart version</a> of the top Toni Morrison quotations.</p> <h1 id="top-5-novel-titles-mentioned-in-tweets">Top 5 Novel Titles Mentioned in Tweets</h1> <p>Many of the Twitter users featured in this archive shouted out their first-read, favorite, or most memorable Toni Morrison novel by name. To see which novels were mentioned the most, I identified tweets that included Morrison’s fiction titles in a capitalized or all-caps form (generally indicating the proper noun usage of the word or words).</p> <p><a href="../../../assets/img/morrison/top_5_novels_toni_morrison_tweets.png"><img width="100%" alt="Common Quotations in Toni Morrison Tweets" src="../../../assets/img/morrison/top_5_novels.png"/></a></p> <p>The top five Morrison novels mentioned on Twitter after her death appeared to be <em>Beloved</em> (1987), <em>Song of Solomon</em> (1977), <em>The Bluest Eye</em> (1970), <em>Sula</em> (1973), and <em>A Mercy</em> (2008). All eleven of Morrison’s novels were mentioned within these roughly million tweets, however, and you can also explore a <a href="../../../assets/img/morrison/all_novels_toni_morrison_tweets.png">bar chart that compares mentions of all her novels</a>.</p> <h1 id="top-emojis-in-tweets">Top Emojis in Tweets</h1> <ol> <li><big>❤</big> 14,106 tweets</li> <li><big>💔</big> 6,510 tweets</li> <li><big>🙏🏾</big> 6,070 tweets</li> <li><big>🖤</big> 4,611 tweets</li> <li><big>😭</big> 4,055 tweets</li> <li><big>📚</big> 3,745 tweets</li> <li><big>😢</big> 3,517 tweets</li> <li><big>🙏</big> 3,333 tweets</li> <li><big>🕊</big> 3,027 tweets</li> <li><big>✨</big> 2,396 tweets</li> </ol> <h1 id="top-tweets-from-most-followed-accounts">Top Tweets From Most Followed Accounts</h1> <p>Toni Morrison was a truly colossal public figure. So I was also interested in seeing which other highly influential public figures were discussing her after her death. The Twitter accounts with the most followers that also tweeted about Morrison between August 6-7 were Barack Obama, Hillary Clinton, Oprah, <em>The New Yorker</em>, Bernie Sanders, NPR, Common, Kerry Washington, and Bill Clinton.</p> <ol> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Toni Morrison was a national treasure, as good a storyteller, as captivating, in person as she was on the page. Her writing was a beautiful, meaningful challenge to our conscience and our moral imagination. What a gift to breathe the same air as her, if only for a while. <a href="https://t.co/JG7Jgu4p9t">pic.twitter.com/JG7Jgu4p9t</a></p>&mdash; Barack Obama (@BarackObama) <a href="https://twitter.com/BarackObama/status/1158764847800213507?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">August 6, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;If there is a book that you want to read but it hasn&#39;t been written yet, you must be the one to write it,&quot; Toni Morrison said. <br/><br/>We are all so lucky to live in a world where she took her own advice and shared it with others.</p>&mdash; Hillary Clinton (@HillaryClinton) <a href="https://twitter.com/HillaryClinton/status/1158760485040414721?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">August 6, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="et" dir="ltr">Toni Morrison 🙏🏾 <a href="https://t.co/nVjs88kTeg">pic.twitter.com/nVjs88kTeg</a></p>&mdash; Oprah Winfrey (@Oprah) <a href="https://twitter.com/Oprah/status/1158798957834690560?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">August 6, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Toni Morrison has died, at eighty-eight. In 2017, she wrote about her father&#39;s philosophy on work and the four points she took to heart. <a href="https://t.co/0xi6kMI3Hq">https://t.co/0xi6kMI3Hq</a> <a href="https://t.co/ZId3nzhVVh">pic.twitter.com/ZId3nzhVVh</a></p>&mdash; The New Yorker (@NewYorker) <a href="https://twitter.com/NewYorker/status/1158784271529730051?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">August 6, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;If you are free, you need to free somebody else. If you have some power, then your job is to empower somebody else.&quot; -Toni Morrison<br/><br/>Today we lost an American legend. May she rest in peace. <a href="https://t.co/DInZvd8stY">https://t.co/DInZvd8stY</a></p>&mdash; Bernie Sanders (@BernieSanders) <a href="https://twitter.com/BernieSanders/status/1158762920374931459?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">August 6, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Toni Morrison&#39;s books focus, without apology or explanation, on black lives.<br/><br/>&quot;I&#39;ve spent my entire writing life trying to make sure that the white gaze was not the dominant one in any of my books,&quot; she told Charlie Rose in 1998.<br/><br/>Morrison has died at 88.<a href="https://t.co/E7KN4fQelX">https://t.co/E7KN4fQelX</a></p>&mdash; NPR (@NPR) <a href="https://twitter.com/NPR/status/1158743445940461568?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">August 6, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">“We die. That may be the meaning of life. But we do language. That may be the measure of our lives.” Toni Morrison. I’m deeply sadden to share that one of our greatest writers and minds in American History, Toni Morrison, passed away at the age of 88. May God Bless Her Soul. <a href="https://t.co/Dq1UL4ENIY">pic.twitter.com/Dq1UL4ENIY</a></p>&mdash; COMMON (@common) <a href="https://twitter.com/common/status/1158769613221400576?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">August 6, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">“You wanna fly, you got to give up the shit that weighs you down.”<br/>Toni Morrison. <br/><br/>I cannot imagine growing up in a world without her words. I pray you rest In Peace and in Power. <br/>We will celebrate you with endless gratitude and love. Always.</p>&mdash; kerry washington (@kerrywashington) <a href="https://twitter.com/kerrywashington/status/1158757608037031936?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">August 6, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;Racism will disappear when [it&#39;s] no longer profitable and no longer psychologically useful. When that happens, it&#39;ll be gone&quot; — Toni Morrison speaking to NPR&#39;s Michel Martin in a 2008 interview about her book, &quot;A Mercy.&quot; <a href="https://t.co/7vF7xcWrT7">pic.twitter.com/7vF7xcWrT7</a></p>&mdash; NPR (@NPR) <a href="https://twitter.com/NPR/status/1158784988948684800?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">August 6, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Toni Morrison was a world-class human being. Her words stirred our souls &amp; challenged our consciences to confront injustice, large or small, wherever it exists. How blessed we are that she gave us her gifts. Hillary and I are grateful for her life and the kindness she showed us. <a href="https://t.co/ZCSPFCma1F">pic.twitter.com/ZCSPFCma1F</a></p>&mdash; Bill Clinton (@BillClinton) <a href="https://twitter.com/BillClinton/status/1158805694759481345?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">August 6, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> </ol> <h1 id="to-access-the-toni-morrison-tweet-archive">To Access the Toni Morrison Tweet Archive</h1> <p>Twitter’s terms of service do not allow tweet datasets to be shared openly on the web, but they do allow for the sharing of unique identifiers, which are tethered to every tweet and which can be used to access an original tweet if that tweet is still public and has not been deleted yet. This policy, <a href="https://www.docnow.io/catalog/">as DocNow puts it</a>, “speaks to users rights as content creators, while also allowing researchers to share their data with others.” Accordingly, I have shared a <a href="https://archive.org/details/toni-morrison-tweets">data set</a> of 1,170,032 unique identifiers for tweets that mentioned “Toni Morrison” with or without a space between August 6 and August 9, 2019 on the Internet Archive. It will also be available through <a href="https://www.docnow.io/catalog/">DocNow’s Tweet ID Catalogue</a>.</p> <p>If you want to access and analyze this data yourself, you can do so with <a href="https://github.com/DocNow/twarc">twarc</a> or the desktop application, <a href="https://github.com/DocNow/hydrator">Hydrator</a> (and the “hydration” process is explained in greater detail in both places). If you choose to use this data, I highly recommend consulting <a href="https://www.docnow.io/docs/docnow-whitepaper-2018.pdf">DocNow’s white paper</a> about archiving social media content, especially their concluding recommendations:</p> <blockquote> <ol> <li>Archivists should engage and work with the communities they wish to document.</li> <li>Documentation efforts must go beyond what can be collected without permission from the web and social media.</li> <li>Archivists should follow social media platforms’ terms of service where they are congruent with the values of the communities they are attempting to document.</li> <li>When possible, archivists should apply traditional archival practices such as appraisal, collection development, and donor relations to social media and web materials.</li> </ol> </blockquote> <h1 id="reconstituting-and-rereading-tonimorrison">Reconstituting and Rereading Toni Morrison</h1> <p>The loss of Toni Morrison is a profound one. Like so many others, I am drawn to Obama’s widely recirculated words to put this loss into perspective. It really does feel like a “gift” to have “breathe[d] the same air” as the great Toni Morrison, “if only for a while.” It’s hard to imagine that a more major literary figure will be alive again during my lifetime.</p> <p>But it is also profound to have witnessed so many people testifying to Morrison’s literary influence and legacy this week, to have seen such sincere interest in her life and work, and to have observed the author reconstituted by those mourning and celebrating her on Twitter. These Twitter users collectively grieved Morrison—the author of deep, <a href="https://slate.com/culture/2019/03/toni-morrison-difficulty-black-women.html">difficult</a>, and complex narratives—in the necessarily reductive form of 240-character tweets, photos, and video clips, and they often did so with creativity, beauty, and power.</p> <p>Many of these Twitter users also spoke about returning to Morrison’s difficult novels (or essays or literary criticism) or about wanting to dive into them for the first time. There have been many <a href="https://time.com/5645078/toni-morrison-books/">“essential” Toni Morrison reading lists</a> published in the last few days, but I wanted to conclude by offering a short round-up of further scholarly reading on Morrison to also direct people to the work of scholars who have been studying and attending to Toni Morrison’s life and literature for many years now.</p> <p>Barbara Hill Rigney, <a href="https://ohiostatepress.org/books/BookPages/RigneyVoices.htm"><em>The Voices of Toni Morrison</em></a> (1991).<br/> Trudier Harris, <a href="http://utpress.org/title/fiction-and-folklore/"><em>Fiction and Folklore: The Novels of Toni Morrison</em></a> (1991).<br/> David L. Middleton, ed., <a href="https://www.taylorfrancis.com/books/9781315864303"><em>Toni Morrison’s Fiction: Contemporary Criticism</em></a> (1997).<br/> Nancy J. Peterson, ed., <a href="https://jhupbooks.press.jhu.edu/title/toni-morrison"><em>Toni Morrison: Critical and Theoretical Approaches</em></a> (1997). <br/> John N. Duvall, <a href="https://www.palgrave.com/us/book/9780312234027"><em>The Identifying Fictions of Toni Morrison: Modernist Authenticity and Postmodern Blackness</em></a> (2000).<br/> Lucille Fultz, <a href="https://www.press.uillinois.edu/books/catalog/69pka8nx9780252028236.html"><em>Toni Morrison: Playing with Difference</em></a> (2003).<br/> Justine Tally, ed., <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/cambridge-companion-to-toni-morrison/C93B7CBEF632F83D29969D388E6B3CAE"><em>The Cambridge Companion to Toni Morrison</em></a> (2008).<br/> Stephanie Li, <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Toni-Morrison-Biography-Greenwood-Biographies/dp/0313378398"><em>Toni Morrison: A Biography</em></a> (2009).<br/> Evelyn Jaffe Schreiber, <a href="https://lsupress.org/books/detail/race-trauma-and-home-in-the-novels-of-toni-morrison/"><em>Race, Trauma, and Home in the Novels of Toni Morrison</em></a> (2010).<br/> Tessa Roynon, <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/cambridge-introduction-to-toni-morrison/9E5D43B89BABCED472505C99C6D449E4"><em>The Cambridge Introduction to Toni Morrison</em></a> (2012).<br/> Juda Bennett, <a href="https://www.sunypress.edu/p-5932-toni-morrison-and-the-queer-ple.aspx"><em>Toni Morrison and the Queer Pleasure of Ghosts</em></a> (2014).</p> <h1 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h1> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote"> <p>There were actually 1,001,518 tweets and retweets that mentioned Toni Morrison’s name within this period. By the time that I began hydrating them on August 8, however, there were only 976,014 tweets that were still public and not deleted. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="twitter"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Toni Morrison, one of the best and most influential literary writers of the 20th and 21st centuries, died on Monday. She was the first Black woman to win the Nobel Prize in literature and the author of eleven novels, dozens of essays, as well as literary criticism. When Morrison’s publisher announced the news of her death on Tuesday morning, thousands of people began mourning her incredible life on Twitter. Within a little over a day, more than 500,000 Twitter users in fact cited Toni Morrison specifically by first and last name in a million tweets and retweets.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mourning Mary Oliver in 100,000+ Tweets</title><link href="https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2019/mourning-mary-oliver-in-tweets/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mourning Mary Oliver in 100,000+ Tweets"/><published>2019-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2019/mourning-mary-oliver-in-tweets</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2019/mourning-mary-oliver-in-tweets/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> <p>I saw her lift her honeyed muzzle<br/> into the leaves, and her thick arms, <br/> as though she would fly -<br/> an enormous bee<br/> all sweetness and wings -<br/> -Mary Oliver, “Happiness”</p> </blockquote> <p>Last month on my birthday, my boyfriend’s mom sent me a handwritten Mary Oliver poem in the mail. The poem, called “Happiness,” is about a she-bear getting a little bit drunk on honey. It was a lovely gift in every way.</p> <p>I’m obsessed with how people share literature with one another, whether it’s through handwritten notes, or well-worn library books, or tweets. So when <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/01/17/obituaries/mary-oliver-dead.html">Mary Oliver died on Thursday</a>, I was sad but also blown away by how many people were mourning her life by sharing her words on social media.</p> <p>When I checked Twitter, I found an outpouring of Oliver’s poetry. Friends, colleagues, celebrities, and strangers were tweeting favorite quotations, pictures of dog-eared pages, and videos of themselves reciting her words. This free-flowing, social circulation seemed like a fitting tribute to a poet whose work has for so long been dedicated to and beloved by a wide public.</p> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">“When it&#39;s over, I want to say all my life I was a bride married to amazement.” Mary Oliver<br/> I’ve been soothed, comforted, informed, enhanced by your words. Your life has been a Blessing to the world. <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/maryoliver?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#maryoliver</a></p>&mdash; Oprah Winfrey (@Oprah) <a href="https://twitter.com/Oprah/status/1085971890940698624?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 17, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <p><br/> I decided to start archiving tweets that mentioned Mary Oliver’s name early Thursday afternoon. To do so, I used <a href="https://www.docnow.io/">DocNow</a>’s awesome archiving tool, <a href="https://github.com/DocNow/twarc">twarc</a>. Within the last few days, over 100,000 tweets and retweets from 78,000+ users in 38 different languages have acknowledged Mary Oliver. Here’s a breakdown of the archive so far:</p> <p><strong>Tweets Collected:</strong> 117,055 <br/> <strong>Users:</strong> 78,093 <br/> <strong>Languages:</strong> 38<br/> <strong>Tweets with Images</strong>: 21,401 (18.28%)<br/> <strong>Type of Tweets</strong>: 87,856 retweets (75%), 20,126 original (17%), 7,274 quotes (6%), 1,799 replies (2%)<br/> <strong>Earliest Tweet:</strong> 12:20PM (CST) 01-17-2019 <br/> <strong>Latest Tweet:</strong> 9:15AM (CST) 01-19-2019 <br/> <strong>Total Duration of Archive:</strong> 1 day, 21 hours</p> <p>I’ve shared the tweet ids for this <a href="https://github.com/melaniewalsh/Mary-Oliver-Tweets">Mary Oliver archive on my GitHub page</a>, so if you’d like to analyze the data yourself, you just have to “rehydrate” the ids. You can do so with <a href="https://github.com/DocNow/twarc">twarc</a> or with the desktop application, <a href="https://github.com/DocNow/hydrator">Hydrator</a> (and the 💦💦💦 process is explained on both of those pages). I plan to keep the livestream capture going for the next couple weeks, and I will update the archive accordingly.</p> <p>But for now I wanted to share an overview of these 100,000+ Mary Oliver tweets, including the most retweeted tweets, the most common phrases used, the top images, and the biggest celebrity shout-outs:</p> <h1 id="top-10-most-retweeted">Top 10 Most Retweeted</h1> <ol> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Thank you, Mary Oliver, for giving so many of us words to live by.<br/><br/>&quot;Tell me, what is it you plan to do<br/>with your one wild and precious life?&quot;</p>&mdash; Hillary Clinton (@HillaryClinton) <a href="https://twitter.com/HillaryClinton/status/1085949334288584704?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 17, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">The Uses of Sorrow<br/>by Mary Oliver<br/><br/>(In my sleep I dreamed this poem)<br/><br/>Someone I loved once gave me<br/>a box full of darkness.<br/><br/>It took me years to understand<br/>that this, too, was a gift.</p>&mdash; Sarah Kay (@kaysarahsera) <a href="https://twitter.com/kaysarahsera/status/1085946797132996608?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 17, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">“Doesn’t everything die at last, and too soon?”<br/><br/>Mary Oliver: <a href="https://t.co/KumCX5vfL6">pic.twitter.com/KumCX5vfL6</a></p>&mdash; Rachel Mennies (@rmennies) <a href="https://twitter.com/rmennies/status/1085930924607451138?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 17, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">RIP Mary Oliver, your words will live on <a href="https://t.co/WEZ3KtLvoq">pic.twitter.com/WEZ3KtLvoq</a></p>&mdash; rachel syme (@rachsyme) <a href="https://twitter.com/rachsyme/status/1085929267765149701?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 17, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Snow was falling, so much like stars filling the dark trees.<br/>Mary Oliver <a href="https://t.co/glSQ4vLWJG">pic.twitter.com/glSQ4vLWJG</a></p>&mdash; ADF (@AlinaDal_F) <a href="https://twitter.com/AlinaDal_F/status/825960547191517184?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 30, 2017</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;Poetry isn&#39;t a profession, it&#39;s a way of life. It&#39;s an empty basket; you put your life into it and make something out of that.&quot;<br/><br/>RIP Mary Oliver, filler of baskets. <a href="https://t.co/TmyzPOCjyf">pic.twitter.com/TmyzPOCjyf</a></p>&mdash; Literary Hub (@lithub) <a href="https://twitter.com/lithub/status/1085931241910792194?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 17, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">The poet Mary Oliver died today. Her poetry spoke — with a calm &amp; tender lucidity — of commonalities that joined human hearts to the more-than-human world. <a href="https://t.co/X0CaDwb1Hr">pic.twitter.com/X0CaDwb1Hr</a></p>&mdash; Robert Macfarlane (@RobGMacfarlane) <a href="https://twitter.com/RobGMacfarlane/status/1086000078718988289?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 17, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Mary Oliver was my favorite poet. Heartbroken to learn of her death. Grateful she gave us what she did with her one wild and precious life. <a href="https://t.co/3GJhVAbtMP">pic.twitter.com/3GJhVAbtMP</a></p>&mdash; Misha Collins (@mishacollins) <a href="https://twitter.com/mishacollins/status/1085986611416817664?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 17, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">JUST IN: Poet Mary Oliver has died at 83. Oliver won the Pulitzer Prize and the National Book Award for poems about nature and animals which made her one of this country’s best-selling poets. To be understood, poetry &quot;mustn&#39;t be fancy,&quot; she once told NPR.<a href="https://t.co/tEUiwq4pck">https://t.co/tEUiwq4pck</a></p>&mdash; NPR (@NPR) <a href="https://twitter.com/NPR/status/1085938799782199297?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 17, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">“It doesn’t have to be blue iris, it can be weeds in a vacant lot. <br/><br/>Just pay attention, then patch a few words together and don’t try to make them elaborate. <br/><br/>This isn’t a contest but the doorway into thanks. A silence in which another voice may speak.” <br/><br/>- Mary Oliver, Praying <a href="https://t.co/SHh1EYdU6T">pic.twitter.com/SHh1EYdU6T</a></p>&mdash; Ava DuVernay (@ava) <a href="https://twitter.com/ava/status/1085950627233046533?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 17, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> </ol> <p>These top tweets all quote Oliver’s poetry or words in some way. They cite the poems <a href="https://www.poets.org/poetsorg/poem/wild-geese">“Wild Geese”</a>, <a href="https://www.loc.gov/poetry/180/133.html">“The Summer Day”</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/kaysarahsera/status/1085946797132996608?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">“The Uses of Sorrow”</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/ava/status/1085950627233046533?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">“Praying”</a>, and <a href="https://sacredtremor.com/blog/snowy-night-mary-oliver">“Snowy Night”</a>, as well as two famous quips about poetry itself: that it “isn’t a profession” and that it “mustn’t be fancy.” I used key phrases from these 10 quotations—e.g., “one wild and precious life,” “box full of darkness,” “wild geese”—to see how often these same poems/words were cited:</p> <p><a href="../../../assets/img/mary-oliver-quotes-bigger-font.png"><img width="100%" alt="Poems/Words Quoted in Mary Oliver Tweets" src="../../../assets/img/mary-oliver-quotes-bigger-font.png"/></a></p> <p>The above chart does not represent all citations of Oliver’s words, just the specific phrases/poems that I searched for. Most other tweets in the corpus (95,598 tweets) were not included or identified here.</p> <h1 id="most-common-phrases-used">Most Common Phrases Used</h1> <p>I also searched for the most common recurring phrases, which again resurfaced quotations from “The Summer Day,” “Wild Geese,” and “The Uses of Sorrow.” But this search also turned up other widely-cited quotations, such as “To live in this world/you must be able/to do three things” from <a href="https://readalittlepoetry.wordpress.com/2005/09/12/in-blackwater-woods-by-mary-oliver/">“In Blackwater Woods”</a>.</p> <ol> <li>“what is it you plan to do with your one wild and precious life”</li> <li>“someone i loved once gave me a box full of darkness”</li> <li>“thank you mary oliver for giving so many of us words to live by”</li> <li>“(in my sleep i dreamed this poem)”</li> <li>“to live in this world you must be able to do three things”</li> <li>“doesn’t everything die at last, and too soon”</li> <li>“pay attention be astonished tell about it”</li> <li>“i was a bride married to amazement”</li> <li>“the poet mary oliver died”</li> <li>“no matter how lonely you are the world offers itself to your imagination”</li> </ol> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">To live in this world<br/><br/>you must be able<br/>to do three things:<br/>to love what is mortal;<br/>to hold it<br/><br/>against your bones knowing<br/>your own life depends on it;<br/>and, when the time comes to let it go,<br/>to let it go.<br/><br/>—Mary Oliver, RIP<a href="https://t.co/gnyMu3Jocw">https://t.co/gnyMu3Jocw</a></p>&mdash; Jen Benka (@jenbenka) <a href="https://twitter.com/jenbenka/status/1085949629236154372?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 17, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Pay attention.<br/>Be astonished. <br/>Tell about it. <br/><br/>—Mary Oliver <a href="https://t.co/H3yYlWwqdy">pic.twitter.com/H3yYlWwqdy</a></p>&mdash; Alice Anderson (@AlicePoet) <a href="https://twitter.com/AlicePoet/status/1085941996504604674?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 17, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <p><b></b></p> <h1 id="top-images-click-to-enlarge">Top Images (click to enlarge):</h1> <p>To look for Oliver’s poetry only within the text of tweets misses one of the major ways that her words were shared: images and videos. The following shows the top images from Mary Oliver tweets, all pictures of text except for <a href="https://twitter.com/mishacollins/status/1086013194294853632">one snap of the actor Misha Collins</a>, who is an apparent Oliver disciple and otherwise most famous for his role on the television show <em>Supernatural</em>.</p> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td><a href="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/DxIAauQW0AE6IZo.jpg"><img width="1604" alt="" src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/DxIAauQW0AE6IZo.jpg"/></a></td> <td><a href="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/DxH-2hwXcAo4zwW.jpg"><img width="1604" alt=" " src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/DxH-2hwXcAo4zwW.jpg"/></a></td> <td><a href="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/DxIAQlGW0AIMMuh.jpg"><img width="1604" alt=" " src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/DxIAQlGW0AIMMuh.jpg"/></a></td> </tr> <tr> <td><a href="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/DxImZ5jVsAErmsT.jpg"><img width="1604" alt=" " src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/DxImZ5jVsAErmsT.jpg"/></a></td> <td><a href="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/DxJH0XSUwAEyUfq.jpg"><img width="1604" alt=" " src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/DxJH0XSUwAEyUfq.jpg"/></a></td> <td><a href="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/DxJLEyGU8AE-KUn.jpg"><img width="1604" alt=" " src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/DxJLEyGU8AE-KUn.jpg"/></a></td> </tr> <tr> <td><a href="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/DxIERi-WwAI1lcR.jpg"><img width="1604" alt="" src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/DxIERi-WwAI1lcR.jpg"/></a></td> <td><a href="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/DxIJfBKXcAApXW6.jpg"><img width="1604" alt=" " src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/DxIJfBKXcAApXW6.jpg"/></a></td> <td><a href="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/DxIGhbgVAAAqAts.jpg"><img width="1604" alt="" src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/DxIGhbgVAAAqAts.jpg"/></a></td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <h1 id="top-twitter-celeb-shout-outs">Top Twitter Celeb Shout-outs</h1> <p>Speaking of actors who adore Mary Oliver, the following shows the individuals with the most Twitter followers who mentioned her name in the last few days (in order of most to least followers):</p> <ol> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">“When it&#39;s over, I want to say all my life I was a bride married to amazement.” Mary Oliver<br/> I’ve been soothed, comforted, informed, enhanced by your words. Your life has been a Blessing to the world. <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/maryoliver?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#maryoliver</a></p>&mdash; Oprah Winfrey (@Oprah) <a href="https://twitter.com/Oprah/status/1085971890940698624?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 17, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">To all of my kindred spirits who dare to dream and create 💗🙏🏽💗 <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/maryoliver?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#maryoliver</a> had such a beautiful way of telling the truth of a full and meaningful life through her poetry✨<a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ripmaryoliver?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#ripmaryoliver</a> <a href="https://t.co/ScA2UTIcGj">https://t.co/ScA2UTIcGj</a></p>&mdash; Jessica Alba (@jessicaalba) <a href="https://twitter.com/jessicaalba/status/1086429985840058368?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 19, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Patron saint of the lost but brave ... <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/MaryOliver?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#MaryOliver</a> <a href="https://t.co/O8zMq8rEOJ">pic.twitter.com/O8zMq8rEOJ</a></p>&mdash; Lena Dunham (@lenadunham) <a href="https://twitter.com/lenadunham/status/1086046117928697857?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 17, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">“I made a world out of words. And it was my salvation.” RIP Mary Oliver. <a href="https://t.co/TneWooytLO">pic.twitter.com/TneWooytLO</a></p>&mdash; AJ (@TheAJMendez) <a href="https://twitter.com/TheAJMendez/status/1086083744027467777?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 18, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">R.I.P. poet Mary Oliver:: “Instructions for living a life. Pay attention. Be astonished. Tell about it.” <a href="https://t.co/KieSs46WuV">pic.twitter.com/KieSs46WuV</a></p>&mdash; RainnWilson (@rainnwilson) <a href="https://twitter.com/rainnwilson/status/1086312421407375360?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 18, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">My love knows me and today is a sad day...saying goodbye to <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/maryoliver?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#maryoliver</a>...rest in peace and thank you for your legacy. <br/><br/>Her words bring light into every room in which they whisper....🎆 <a href="https://t.co/8PRfRS6pn7">https://t.co/8PRfRS6pn7</a></p>&mdash; Sara Bareilles (@SaraBareilles) <a href="https://twitter.com/SaraBareilles/status/1086071882548301825?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 18, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Thinking of Mary Oliver today. What will you do with your one wild &amp; precious life? <a href="https://t.co/UXYytu1Uyq">pic.twitter.com/UXYytu1Uyq</a></p>&mdash; Misha Collins (@mishacollins) <a href="https://twitter.com/mishacollins/status/1086013194294853632?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 17, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Oh Mary Oliver, how can we ever say a deep enough thank you? Dear God, please bless her soul. May her words continue to inspire us, and may all of us walk in her footsteps.<a href="https://t.co/k6D1M8Ataq">https://t.co/k6D1M8Ataq</a></p>&mdash; Marianne Williamson (@marwilliamson) <a href="https://twitter.com/marwilliamson/status/1086012215386361858?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 17, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Thank you Mary Oliver for your beautiful healing work. Forever grateful. RIP <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/wildgeese?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#wildgeese</a></p>&mdash; Miranda Hart (@mermhart) <a href="https://twitter.com/mermhart/status/1085976667498209280?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 17, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> <li> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">I Raise A Glass and Shed a tear to the passing of one of my favorite poets...........Mary Oliver. Her words were a bridge from Nature to the Spiritual World................♥️ God Bless You Mary! <a href="https://t.co/loT4siZqdO">pic.twitter.com/loT4siZqdO</a></p>&mdash; Madonna (@Madonna) <a href="https://twitter.com/Madonna/status/1085992586702139399?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 17, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </li> </ol> <h1 id="mourning-mary-oliverscreenshots-selfies-snail-mail">Mourning Mary Oliver—Screenshots, Selfies, Snail Mail</h1> <p>This post only scratches the surface of how folks mourned Mary Oliver on Twitter in the wake of her death. But it’s been my small way of fulfilling Oliver’s edict: to pay attention, to be astonished, to tell about it.</p> <p>I’m telling you that I’m astonished to see tens of thousands of Twitter users sharing poetry with each other in the span of two days. Here’s to sharing more poetry with one another—and, of course, to Mary Oliver.</p> <p><a href="../../../assets/img/Happiness-Mary-Oliver.jpg"><img width="100%" alt="Happiness" src="../../../assets/img/Happiness-Mary-Oliver.jpg"/></a></p> <p><b></b></p> <p><em>If you’re interested in exploring this archive for yourself, you can download the data by using the <a href="https://github.com/melaniewalsh/Mary-Oliver-Tweets">tweet ids on my GitHub page</a>.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="twitter"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I saw her lift her honeyed muzzle into the leaves, and her thick arms, as though she would fly - an enormous bee all sweetness and wings - -Mary Oliver, “Happiness”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Things That The U.S. Presidents Described as “Great” in Their Inaugural Addresses</title><link href="https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2017/president-great-things/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Things That The U.S. Presidents Described as “Great” in Their Inaugural Addresses"/><published>2017-02-01T21:29:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-02-01T21:29:00+00:00</updated><id>https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2017/president-great-things</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2017/president-great-things/"><![CDATA[<p>For the February 2017 meeting of the <a href="http://sites.wustl.edu/darg">Digital Approaches Reading Group</a> (DARG), which I help co-convene at WashU, we explored 58 Presidential Inaugural Addresses as a common dataset — in the hopes of collectively showcasing and experimenting with different DH methodologies and tools. I was personally curious about a tiny word that I suspected might have big(ly?) implications: the word “great.”</p> <p>President Trump concluded his 2017 Inaugural Address with his now trademark phrase “Make America Great Again”:</p> <blockquote> <p>“Together, we will make America strong again. We will make America wealthy again. We will make America proud again. We will make America safe again. And yes, together, we will make America <em>great</em> again.”</p> </blockquote> <p>The adjective “great” is one of the cornerstones of Trump’s rhetoric, showing up in speeches and tweets to describe things as various as policy meetings, The Apprentice, the threat of CNN, and the proposed Mexican border wall:</p> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Great meeting with CEOs of leading U.S. health insurance companies who provide great healthcare to the American people. <a href="https://t.co/s2NMVMvQq3">pic.twitter.com/s2NMVMvQq3</a></p>&mdash; Donald J. Trump (@realDonaldTrump) <a href="https://twitter.com/realDonaldTrump/status/836261209540288513">February 27, 2017</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">FAKE NEWS media knowingly doesn&#39;t tell the truth. A great danger to our country. The failing <a href="https://twitter.com/nytimes">@nytimes</a> has become a joke. Likewise <a href="https://twitter.com/CNN">@CNN</a>. Sad!</p>&mdash; Donald J. Trump (@realDonaldTrump) <a href="https://twitter.com/realDonaldTrump/status/835325771858251776">February 25, 2017</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">I am reading that the great border WALL will cost more than the government originally thought, but I have not gotten involved in the.....</p>&mdash; Donald J. Trump (@realDonaldTrump) <a href="https://twitter.com/realDonaldTrump/status/830405706255912960">February 11, 2017</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Arnold Schwarzenegger isn&#39;t voluntarily leaving the Apprentice, he was fired by his bad (pathetic) ratings, not by me. Sad end to great show</p>&mdash; Donald J. Trump (@realDonaldTrump) <a href="https://twitter.com/realDonaldTrump/status/838016045222854656">March 4, 2017</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <p>I wanted to explore how previous Presidents had used the word “great” before him. Could I find a historical precedent for this adjective and/or a trajectory of its shifting ideological value?</p> <h1 id="methodology">Methodology</h1> <p>I used the Python module TextBlob, specifically its part-of-speech tagger and ngrams function, to isolate all the nouns that came immediately before or after the word “great” in every speech. Here are the top 10 things that were most commonly described as “great” across all inaugural addresses and the top Presidents who used the word:</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th style="text-align: center"> </th> <th style="text-align: center">word</th> <th style="text-align: center">total # in all addresses</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">1</td> <td style="text-align: center">nation</td> <td style="text-align: center">10</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">2</td> <td style="text-align: center">people</td> <td style="text-align: center">8</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">3</td> <td style="text-align: center">interests</td> <td style="text-align: center">6</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">4</td> <td style="text-align: center">body</td> <td style="text-align: center">4</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">5</td> <td style="text-align: center">objects</td> <td style="text-align: center">4</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">6</td> <td style="text-align: center">wealth</td> <td style="text-align: center">3</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">7</td> <td style="text-align: center">evil</td> <td style="text-align: center">3</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">8</td> <td style="text-align: center">object</td> <td style="text-align: center">3</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">9</td> <td style="text-align: center">republic</td> <td style="text-align: center">3</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">10</td> <td style="text-align: center">responsibilities</td> <td style="text-align: center">3</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p><b></b></p> <p><b></b></p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th style="text-align: center"> </th> <th style="text-align: center">President</th> <th style="text-align: center">total # of “great” as noun modifier</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">1</td> <td style="text-align: center">James Monroe</td> <td style="text-align: center">35</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">2</td> <td style="text-align: center">William Henry Harrison</td> <td style="text-align: center">16</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">3</td> <td style="text-align: center">William McKinley</td> <td style="text-align: center">13</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">4</td> <td style="text-align: center">Woodrow Wilson</td> <td style="text-align: center">10</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">5</td> <td style="text-align: center">Andrew Garfield</td> <td style="text-align: center">10</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">6</td> <td style="text-align: center">Calvin Coolidge</td> <td style="text-align: center">10</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">7</td> <td style="text-align: center">Benjamin Harrison</td> <td style="text-align: center">9</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">8</td> <td style="text-align: center">Franklin D. Roosevelt</td> <td style="text-align: center">8</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">9</td> <td style="text-align: center">William Howard Taft</td> <td style="text-align: center">8</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">10</td> <td style="text-align: center">James Pierce</td> <td style="text-align: center">8</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">11</td> <td style="text-align: center">Ruherford B. Hayes</td> <td style="text-align: center">6</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">12</td> <td style="text-align: center">George W. Bush</td> <td style="text-align: center">6</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">13</td> <td style="text-align: center">Warren G. Harding</td> <td style="text-align: center">6</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">14</td> <td style="text-align: center">George H. W. Bush</td> <td style="text-align: center">6</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">15</td> <td style="text-align: center">Richard Nixon</td> <td style="text-align: center">6</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">16</td> <td style="text-align: center">James Buchanan</td> <td style="text-align: center">6</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">17</td> <td style="text-align: center">Ulysses S. Grant</td> <td style="text-align: center">5</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">18</td> <td style="text-align: center">Ronald Reagan</td> <td style="text-align: center">5</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">19</td> <td style="text-align: center">Dwight D. Eisenhower</td> <td style="text-align: center">5</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">20</td> <td style="text-align: center">Martin Van Buren</td> <td style="text-align: center">5</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">21</td> <td style="text-align: center">Barack Obama</td> <td style="text-align: center">4</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">22</td> <td style="text-align: center">Donald Trump</td> <td style="text-align: center">4</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p><b></b></p> <p>Surprisingly, Donald Trump didn’t even crack the top 10!</p> <p>I played around with visualizing this data in a number of ways, which included a dendrogram and a radial sunburst.</p> <p><img src="../assets/img/dendrogram.svg" alt="Alt text"/></p> <p>They’re pretty, but ultimately I don’t think they show us all that much about the data. So I also created a semantic network to try and understand which “great” things were connecting which Presidents. I used NetworkX, Gephi, and the Sigma.JS plugin to create this force-directed semantic network and this accompanying <a href="/network/index.html">interactive web version</a>.</p> <p><img src="../../../assets/img/gephi_network.svg" alt="Alt text"/></p> <p>So did the tiny word “great” end up having the big implications that I suspected when I first set out? Well, yes and no. I was surprised to discover, though I really shouldn’t have been, that “great” is an incredibly bland, abstract word, which is used to describe a whole lot of bland, abstract concepts like “people,” “interests,” and “objects.” “Nation,” the word most commonly described as “great,” connects Presidents as disparate as Barack Obama, Richard Nixon, Ulysses S. Grant, Ruherford B. Hayes, James Monroe, Andrew Garfield, George H. W. Bush, Theodore Roosevelt, Franklin D. Roosevelt, and Jimmy Carter. In other words, “great” didn’t reveal as many ideological insights as I first expected. It’s largely used as rhetorical fluff and filler, a vague hand-wavy intensifier.</p> <p>But this lack of meaning <em>is</em> meaningful. It reveals even more clearly, to my mind, that Trump’s “Make America Great Again” slogan is one big empty rhetorical illusion. What exactly does “great” mean? What exactly makes America “great”? A lot is hidden inside this bland banality, as George Orwell would be the first to warn us. In his 1946 essay “Politics and the English Language,” Orwell insists that some of the most insidious, violent politics “consist largely of euphemism, question-begging and sheer cloudy vagueness.”</p> <p>It is curious, however, that Donald Trump is the only President to describe “America” as “great” (at least immediately before or after the word “America”) and suggests that this slogan is a relatively unique coinage. It was much more common to refer to the “nation” or “people” or “republic” as “great” than to refer to “America” as “great,” which perhaps suggests something about our increasingly globalized moment, in which distinguishing “America” from the rest of the world has become more of a routine necessity and, to some, particularly those in the Trump camp, an intense anxiety.</p> <p>Seeing which Presidents are connected by which words is also rather curious, though I’m not entirely sure what to make of it. Donald Trump and George H. W. Bush are connected by the word “men.” Ronald Reagan and Ulysses S. Grant are connected by “honor.” Dwight D. Eisenhower, James Buchanan, and Andrew Garfield are all connected by “evil” (Buchanan also dropped the plural “great evil<em>s</em>”). William McKinley, George W. Bush, and Richard Nixon are all connected by “responsibilities.” James Monroe and John Adams are connected by “satisfaction.” And Harry S. Truman, Bill Clinton, and George Washington aren’t connected to anyone at all.</p> <p>Feel free to explore the network yourself and see what other kinds of connections and/or oddities you can find. I will conclude here with a list of the best/weirdest “great” things in the Inaugural Addresses according to the U.S. Presidents according to me.</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th style="text-align: center"> </th> <th style="text-align: center">top weirdest “great” things as decreed by me in no particular order</th> <th style="text-align: center">President</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">1</td> <td style="text-align: center">blotches</td> <td style="text-align: center">Warren G. Harding</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">2</td> <td style="text-align: center">parties</td> <td style="text-align: center">George H. W. Bush</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">3</td> <td style="text-align: center">dread</td> <td style="text-align: center">William Henry Harrison</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">4</td> <td style="text-align: center">bulwark</td> <td style="text-align: center">William Henry Harrison</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">5</td> <td style="text-align: center">annoyance</td> <td style="text-align: center">James Monroe</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">6</td> <td style="text-align: center">scheme</td> <td style="text-align: center">James Pierce</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">7</td> <td style="text-align: center">inlets</td> <td style="text-align: center">James Monroe</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">8</td> <td style="text-align: center">hands</td> <td style="text-align: center">Andrew Jackson</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">9</td> <td style="text-align: center">satisfaction</td> <td style="text-align: center">John Adams</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">10</td> <td style="text-align: center">rebellion</td> <td style="text-align: center">Ulysses S. Grant</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p><b></b></p> <p>Check out the source code for the project <a href="https://github.com/melaniewalsh/inaugural_addresses">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="text-analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[For the February 2017 meeting of the Digital Approaches Reading Group (DARG), which I help co-convene at WashU, we explored 58 Presidential Inaugural Addresses as a common dataset — in the hopes of collectively showcasing and experimenting with different DH methodologies and tools. I was personally curious about a tiny word that I suspected might have big(ly?) implications: the word “great.”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“The Mythology of James Baldwin on Twitter”</title><link href="https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2016/the-mythology-of-james-baldwin-on-twitter/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“The Mythology of James Baldwin on Twitter”"/><published>2016-11-13T21:29:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-11-13T21:29:00+00:00</updated><id>https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2016/the-mythology-of-james-baldwin-on-twitter</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2016/the-mythology-of-james-baldwin-on-twitter/"><![CDATA[<p><em>The following is a transcript from my paper “Tweets of a Native Son: The Mythology of James Baldwin on Twitter,” which I gave at the <a href="http://www.luc.edu/mmla/convention/">MMLA conference</a> on November 12. Huge thanks to Doug Knox from the <a href="https://hdw.artsci.wustl.edu/">HDW</a> for helping me figure out how to wrangle Twitter data and to <a href="http://mith.umd.edu/people/person/ed-summers/">Ed Summers from MITH</a> for generously sharing data, tools, and thoughtfulness.</em></p> <hr/> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td><img src="../../../assets/img/tobeanegro.jpg" alt="alt text"/> <a href="https://www.behance.net/gallery/23843777/Black-History-Month-in-Its-Own-Words">By Ronald Wimberly</a></td> <td><img src="../../../assets/img/tobeblackandconscious.jpg" alt="alt text"/> <a href="http://jijennin70.tumblr.com/post/121885939190/finally-finished-this-baldwin-piece">By John Ira Jennings</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/jijennings?lang=en">@JIJennings</a></td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p><b></b></p> <p><big>J</big>ames Baldwin is alive and well on Twitter, and literary scholars should be paying attention. Though Baldwin published his last two works in 1985, two years before his death, today he speaks anew on the popular social media platform—and I mean “anew” quite literally. Baldwin’s words are not simply being invoked, referenced, and quoted; they are also being edited, updated, and in some places wholly fabricated. Eddie S. Glaude Jr. and William J. Maxwell have both noted that Baldwin has become one of the leading literary voices of the #BlackLivesMatter movement, considered a clarifying prophetic muse of contemporary American race relations and politics, especially on Twitter, where, as the leading hashtag in #BlackLivesMatter reminds us, this movement largely began and continues to flourish. Both scholars have also asked why. Why Baldwin? Why now? “His words inspire on social media; his phrases speak from T-shirts; his face covers a throw pillow on Etsy,” Glaude writes in an <a href="http://time.com/4457112/james-baldwin-eddie-glaude/">August <em>Time</em> article</a>. “But apart from his marketability—that people can use him as an avatar of supposed seriousness—what does Baldwin offer us in this moment? What does he force us, as Americans, to confront?” My paper seeks to answer these questions and investigate the relationship between Baldwin’s literary legacy and contemporary American racial politics by taking his words on social media seriously and by conducting a large-scale computational analysis of tweets. But why am I, as a literary scholar, taking tweets seriously?</p> <p>First, I’m doing so because I believe that social media data, which has exploded since the early 2000s, composes perhaps the most comprehensive account of readership and marginalia ever available and thus offers great if untapped potential for literary scholars. In his 1986 essay “First Steps Toward a History of Reading,” Robert Darnton lamented the difficulty of studying readership because “documents rarely show readers at work, fashioning meaning from texts” and because “few of them are rich enough to provide even indirect access to the cognitive and affective elements of reading” (7). But social media data offers precisely that kind of access, a kind of public diary of user’s thoughts and feelings. With over 313 million active users monthly and over 500 million tweets published per day, Twitter data offers literary critics an unprecedentedly wide look at how readers beyond the the academy engage with literary works and their authors—how they talk about literature, feel about literature, and use literature in their daily lives to better understand the world around them. My perspective aligns with Lev Manovich’s concept of “cultural analytics” and the mission of the new journal <a href="http://culturalanalytics.org/"><em>Cultural Analytics</em></a>, both of which advocate for a computational approach to the study of culture that takes advantage of the massive amounts of online user-generated content now available and that doesn’t “draw a boundary between (smaller) historical professional artifacts and (bigger) online digital content created by non-professionals”<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> in the way that most digital humanities projects, especially literary-minded ones, generally do. Though exceptional literary works created by exceptional professionals have been the bread and butter of literary studies, I believe that user-generated content from non-professionals produced at these large scales can fundamentally change the way we study readership.</p> <p>Second, Twitter holds particular significance for my study of Baldwin because it’s been the platform most fundamental to the growth of the #BlackLivesMatter movement and represents a rich conversation about race and politics in America conducted by ordinary citizens. The first and third most popular hashtags in Twitter’s ten-year history are, in fact, #Ferguson and #BlackLivesMatter, which, when measured last March, had been tweeted <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/the-switch/wp/2016/03/21/these-are-the-10-most-influential-hashtags-in-honor-of-twitters-birthday/">27,200,000 times and 12,000,000 times</a>, respectively. To investigate Baldwin’s relationship to these hashtags and these movements, my project thus takes as its archive two sets of tweets that were collected in the months following Michael Brown’s shooting in Ferguson, Missouri: 10,441,785 tweets that mentioned “Ferguson” (either upper or lowercase; with or without a hashtag) between August 10, 2014 and August 27, 2014, roughly the two weeks after the shooting; and 7,868,540 tweets that mentioned “Ferguson” between November 11, 2014 and December 10, 2014, roughly the month after Darren Wilson’s non-indictment.<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> These two snapshots represent, as Sarah J. Jackson and Brooke Foucault Welles have claimed in <a href="http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/1369118X.2015.1106571">their study of the hashtag #Ferguson</a>, “national debates about American racism, police profiling and brutality, militarized responses to civil unrest, government corruption and criminal justice,” as well as the time period when the hashtag #BlackLivesMatter first emerged in a significant way and became popularized. Thus I’m framing my study of tweets that mention “Ferguson” as the crucial beginnings of the #BlackLivesMatter movement on Twitter.</p> <p><b></b></p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th> </th> <th> </th> <th> </th> <th> </th> <th> </th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td> </td> <td><strong>August 2014</strong></td> <td> </td> <td><strong>November 2014</strong></td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Tweets:</strong></td> <td>10,441,785</td> <td> </td> <td>7,868,540</td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Users:</strong></td> <td>1,596,104</td> <td> </td> <td>1,761,950</td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Earliest Tweet:</strong></td> <td>2014-08-10</td> <td> </td> <td>2014-11-11</td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Latest Tweet:</strong></td> <td>2014-08-27</td> <td> </td> <td>2014-12-10</td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Total Duration:</strong></td> <td>16 days, 16:31:07</td> <td> </td> <td>28 days, 6:58:25</td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> </tbody> <tbody> <tr> <td><strong>Top Hashtags:</strong></td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>1. ferguson</td> <td>6,422,131</td> <td> </td> <td>1. ferguson</td> <td>3,969,513</td> </tr> <tr> <td>2. mikebrown</td> <td>583,141</td> <td> </td> <td>2. mikebrown</td> <td>188,976</td> </tr> <tr> <td>3. michaelbrown</td> <td>158,552</td> <td> </td> <td>3. ericgarner</td> <td>178,139</td> </tr> <tr> <td>4. justiceformikebrown</td> <td>84,061</td> <td> </td> <td>4. <strong>blacklivesmatter</strong></td> <td><strong>151,749</strong></td> </tr> <tr> <td>5. tcot</td> <td>70,702</td> <td> </td> <td>5. fergusondecision</td> <td>118,405</td> </tr> <tr> <td>6. gaza</td> <td>70,338</td> <td> </td> <td>6. michaelbrown</td> <td>105,607</td> </tr> <tr> <td>7. stl</td> <td>58,662</td> <td> </td> <td>7. tcot</td> <td>99,477</td> </tr> <tr> <td>8. handsupdontshoot</td> <td>47,126</td> <td> </td> <td>8. darrenwilson</td> <td>89,154</td> </tr> <tr> <td>9. darrenwilson</td> <td>40,091</td> <td> </td> <td>9. icantbreathe</td> <td>89,000</td> </tr> <tr> <td>10. fergusonshooting</td> <td>31,643</td> <td> </td> <td>10. shutitdown</td> <td>45,296</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p><b></b></p> <p>After “hydrating” these 17 million tweets using a tool called <a href="https://github.com/DocNow/twarc">twarc</a>—and “hydrating” basically just means retrieving the metadata for these tweets from the Twitter API<sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>—the next step was narrowing the archive to just the tweets that mention both “Ferguson” and “James Baldwin,” and indeed finding out whether these tweets even existed. So I performed a search for any variation of “J Baldwin” or “James Baldwin” (for example: #JamesBaldwin; J BALDWIN; james balwin, etc.) that appeared within the text of a tweet, which returned 1,839 tweets from the first August dataset and 1,393 tweets from the second November dataset.<sup id="fnref:4" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote" rel="footnote">4</a></sup> These searches quantitatively confirm Glaude’s and Maxwell’s claims about Baldwin’s influence, chiefly that James Baldwin was being talked about on Twitter in the aftermath of Ferguson.</p> <p>And yet the James Baldwin conversation represents less than one-percent of the total conversation in either dataset, which serves as a tempering reminder that the scholarly sense of what is dominant in the larger cultural conversation may be skewed by scholarly newsfeeds. These numbers may even seem small enough to dismiss the case for Baldwin’s prominence on Twitter entirely. But when cross-compared to other prominent black writers, Baldwin is far and away the most invoked. The words “James Baldwin” (1,708 tweets) appear more in the August archive than “Claudia Rankine” (416), “Langston Hughes” (281), “Assata Shakur” (130), “Ta-Nehisi Coates” (129), “Toni Morrison” (72), “Teju Cole” (55), “Richard Wright” (50), “Ralph Ellison” (49), and “Amiri Baraka” (10) combined. As far as tweeted literary conversations go, the James Baldwin conversation is a substantial and dominant one.</p> <p>So why does Baldwin appear so much more frequently than other black writers? What about his style, insights, or legacy resonates in this particular historical moment and on this particular platform? Though my larger long-term project seeks to answer these questions from a number of different angles, the first way I have tried to understand Baldwin’s influence is by analyzing the most popular tweets in the archive, the tweets with the highest “retweet_count,” a category that already conveniently exists in the Twitter metadata and records the number of times a tweet has been shared by another user on his or her own timeline, which often (but not always) suggests a kind of endorsement, and thus can be thought of as an index for community consensus about value and resonance.</p> <hr/> <p><b></b></p> <h1 id="top-10-august-retweets"><strong>Top 10 August Retweets:</strong></h1> <p><b></b></p> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;To be Black and conscious in America is to be in a constant state of rage.&quot; - James Baldwin <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; zellie (@zellieimani) <a href="https://twitter.com/zellieimani/status/499871572023586816">August 14, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;To be a Negro in this country and to be relatively conscious is to be in a rage almost all the time.&quot; —James Baldwin <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; Crystal Kayiza (@c_kayiza) <a href="https://twitter.com/c_kayiza/status/498832276667793408">August 11, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">My new article on <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/MikeBrown?src=hash">#MikeBrown</a>, systemic racism and James Baldwin; if of interest, please share.<a href="http://t.co/DxhX3gCnnF">http://t.co/DxhX3gCnnF</a></p>&mdash; Musa Okwonga (@Okwonga) <a href="https://twitter.com/Okwonga/status/500008972016156672">August 14, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">if you&#39;re following <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a>, watch this essential <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/JamesBaldwin?src=hash">#JamesBaldwin</a> testimony in June 1963: <a href="https://t.co/EVTTXgp82s">https://t.co/EVTTXgp82s</a></p>&mdash; Jose Antonio Vargas (@joseiswriting) <a href="https://twitter.com/joseiswriting/status/501231389333667842">August 18, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;This fight begins in the heart&quot;: <a href="https://twitter.com/LailaLalami">@LailaLalami</a> on reading James Baldwin as Ferguson seethes: <a href="http://t.co/pwErhUga3Z">http://t.co/pwErhUga3Z</a></p>&mdash; NPR Books (@nprbooks) <a href="https://twitter.com/nprbooks/status/501866250973478912">August 19, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">‘Not everything that is faced can be changed, but nothing can be changed until it is faced.’ - James Baldwin <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/FERGUSON?src=hash">#FERGUSON</a></p>&mdash; sandrine. (@drineee) <a href="https://twitter.com/drineee/status/503726050258325505">August 25, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr"><a href="http://t.co/mFvaZuMAIw">http://t.co/mFvaZuMAIw</a> Teju Cole&#39;s beautiful &amp; lacerating piece on James Baldwin, the &quot;black body&quot; &amp; the white gaze, <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a> &amp; beyond.</p>&mdash; Joyce Carol Oates (@JoyceCarolOates) <a href="https://twitter.com/JoyceCarolOates/status/503278563056156673">August 23, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">A quote from James Baldwin in a PSA on <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a> that aired during last night’s <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/VMAs?src=hash">#VMAs</a> WATCH: <a href="http://t.co/X0Q7Zs2z3y">http://t.co/X0Q7Zs2z3y</a> <a href="http://t.co/VyMthSXw6c">pic.twitter.com/VyMthSXw6c</a></p>&mdash; SPLC (@splcenter) <a href="https://twitter.com/splcenter/status/503947612299755520">August 25, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;But black people raise their children as a rehearsal for danger.” -James Baldwin <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; Salamishah Tillet (@salamishah) <a href="https://twitter.com/salamishah/status/502105003033894912">August 20, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;White people think that childhood is a rehearsal for success. White people think of themselves as safe.&quot; -James Baldwin <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; Salamishah Tillet (@salamishah) <a href="https://twitter.com/salamishah/status/502104900164386816">August 20, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <p><b></b></p> <hr/> <p><b></b></p> <h1 id="top-10-november-retweets"><strong>Top 10 November Retweets:</strong></h1> <p><b></b></p> <p>[Tweet deleted]</p> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;To be black in America is to be in a constant state of rage.&quot;<br/><br/>-James Baldwin <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/MikeBrown?src=hash">#MikeBrown</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/FergusonTheRoot?src=hash">#FergusonTheRoot</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; Courtney Thornton (@courteroy_) <a href="https://twitter.com/courteroy_/status/537077232599330816">November 25, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">We live in &quot;a civilization which has always glorified violence--unless the Negro had the gun.&quot;--James Baldwin circa 1963 <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; Jose Antonio Vargas (@joseiswriting) <a href="https://twitter.com/joseiswriting/status/537136943318831105">November 25, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;To be black and conscious in america is a constant state of rage&quot; - James Baldwin<a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/noblackjusticenoblackfriday?src=hash">#noblackjusticenoblackfriday</a><a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; Gbenga Akinnagbe (@GbengaAkinnagbe) <a href="https://twitter.com/GbengaAkinnagbe/status/537130288787517442">November 25, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">My article on <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/MikeBrown?src=hash">#MikeBrown</a>, with an important quote from James Baldwin. If of interest, please share. <a href="http://t.co/S5DsNyJAmG">http://t.co/S5DsNyJAmG</a></p>&mdash; Musa Okwonga (@Okwonga) <a href="https://twitter.com/Okwonga/status/537188928923918336">November 25, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">James Baldwin&#39;s prophetic words in 1960<a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/BlackLivesMatter?src=hash">#BlackLivesMatter</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/FergusionDecision?src=hash">#FergusionDecision</a> <a href="http://t.co/G4KX6bRdfF">pic.twitter.com/G4KX6bRdfF</a></p>&mdash; Rahiel Tesfamariam (@RahielT) <a href="https://twitter.com/RahielT/status/537122331597225984">November 25, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;To be a Negro in this country and to be relatively conscious is to be in a rage almost all the time.&quot; —James Baldwin <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; Crystal Kayiza (@c_kayiza) <a href="https://twitter.com/c_kayiza/status/498832276667793408">August 11, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <p>[Tweet deleted]</p> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">“To be a Negro in this country and to be relatively conscious is to be in a rage almost all the time. ” – James Baldwin <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; Yasiel Plug (@Ketchcast) <a href="https://twitter.com/Ketchcast/status/537074466262507520">November 25, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;To be a Negro in this country and to be relatively conscious is to be in a rage almost all the time.&quot; - James Baldwin <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; BlackHistoryStudies (@BlkHistStudies) <a href="https://twitter.com/BlkHistStudies/status/538014453934333952">November 27, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <p><b></b></p> <hr/> <p><br/></p> <p>These lists immediately reveal that users most often invoke Baldwin through quotation. In fact, Twitter users even appear to have a meta-awareness of the influx of Baldwin quotations in the Ferguson conversation:</p> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="fr" dir="ltr">*insert James Baldwin quote* <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; jefe💙🇭🇹 (@heLLobrOOklyn) <a href="https://twitter.com/heLLobrOOklyn/status/499767201826869249">August 14, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">I&#39;m really need ppl to chill with these James Baldwin quotes. I have no interest in being that woke right now <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ferguson?src=hash">#ferguson</a></p>&mdash; Ashley Powell (@_APowPow) <a href="https://twitter.com/_APowPow/status/498925415025872896">August 11, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <p>These lists also reveal that the Baldwin users overwhelmingly invoke is the social critic James Baldwin, not the fiction writer James Baldwin. His essays, interviews, and debates are far and away the most referenced and quoted works, and in fact no quotations from his fiction appear in these lists. But I want to argue that Baldwin’s literary legacy is not unremembered. Instead I believe that Baldwin’s literary legacy is essential to his role as muse for the #BlackLivesMatter movement, and that his intellectual hybridity as both artist and activist is what makes him particularly attractive. Baldwin’s mythos as an imaginative novelist and artistic genius infuses his more aphoristic, more incisive, and thus more tweetable social criticism.</p> <p>Looking at which Baldwin quotes get retweeted most can give us a sense of how Baldwin’s Twitter readers respond to his texts—which texts, which styles, subjects, and tones resonate the most, and from which parts of Baldwin’s career. But what’s perhaps even more revealing for Baldwin’s readership and reception is not just when Baldwin is being quoted but when he is being <em>misquoted</em>, when Baldwin’s words get edited, updated, transformed, or sometimes even fabricated whole cloth by Twitter users, often outstripping real quotations in circulation and popularity. The focus of the rest of my paper today will be on such a misquotation, a particularly curious and widespread misquotation that continues to evolve and negotiate with its original form throughout the archive, ultimately even surpassing its original form in popularity.</p> <p>This quote was originally excerpted from <a href="https://youtu.be/jNpitdJSXWY?t=43s">“The Negro in American Culture,”</a> a group discussion between Baldwin, Langston Hughes, Lorraine Hansberry, Emile Capouya, and Alfred Kazin that aired on the New York radio station WBAI-FM in January of 1961 and was later transcribed in the journal <em>CrossCurrents</em> the following summer: “Well, the first difficulty is really so simple it’s usually overlooked: to be a Negro in this country and to be relatively conscious, is to be in a rage almost all the time.” The very first tweet that appears in the archive quotes from “The Negro in American Culture” verbatim, or at least directly from the transcript:</p> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;To be a Negro in this country and to be relatively conscious is to be in a rage almost all the time. ” ― James Baldwin <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; Renaissance Man (@cjfluker) <a href="https://twitter.com/cjfluker/status/498684414483001344">August 11, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <p>This accurate transcription of the quote appears as the second most popular tweet in the August archive, clearly resonating with Twitter users:</p> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;To be a Negro in this country and to be relatively conscious is to be in a rage almost all the time.&quot; —James Baldwin <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; Crystal Kayiza (@c_kayiza) <a href="https://twitter.com/c_kayiza/status/498832276667793408">August 11, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <p>But an inaccurate version of this quote is, astonishingly, over four times more popular than the accurate transcription of Baldwin’s words, making it the most popular tweet in the August archive:</p> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;To be Black and conscious in America is to be in a constant state of rage.&quot; - James Baldwin <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; zellie (@zellieimani) <a href="https://twitter.com/zellieimani/status/499871572023586816">August 14, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <p>The most popular James Baldwin quote being invoked in the wake of Michael Brown’s death was thus never actually spoken by James Baldwin. Tellingly, the changes, omissions, and additions made to Baldwin’s words are not announced by brackets, ellipses, or paraphrase, but are instead smoothly and subtly elided. Even more evolutions appear in the November archive, again surpassing the original form in popularity.</p> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;To be black in America is to be in a constant state of rage.&quot;<br/><br/>-James Baldwin <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/MikeBrown?src=hash">#MikeBrown</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/FergusonTheRoot?src=hash">#FergusonTheRoot</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; Courtney Thornton (@courteroy_) <a href="https://twitter.com/courteroy_/status/537077232599330816">November 25, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;To be black and conscious in america is a constant state of rage&quot; - James Baldwin<a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/noblackjusticenoblackfriday?src=hash">#noblackjusticenoblackfriday</a><a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; Gbenga Akinnagbe (@GbengaAkinnagbe) <a href="https://twitter.com/GbengaAkinnagbe/status/537130288787517442">November 25, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <p>There’s a temptation to dismiss these misquotations as characteristic of the worst follies of Internet culture, evidence of how easily lies and inaccuracies can spread throughout social media networks, proof of sloppy, irresponsible, and perhaps even sub-literary desecration—“bad readers,” as my colleague Meredith Kelling might say. The recent election cycle has indeed made it clear that social media networks and algorithms are guilty of many of these things, and they often act as echo chambers for preconceived beliefs that cordon off ideological communities of like-minded people and get further and further away from facts. But it is precisely for this reason that I believe studying these misquotations and, more broadly, studying the way that Internet communities make meaning and narratives is so urgently important.</p> <p>Where these misquotations diverge from Baldwin’s actual words, they reveal some of the key tenets, values, and affects of the movement, as they reveal both what these readers <em>hear</em> Baldwin saying and what they <em>want</em> or <em>need</em> him to say, making this space a site of both interpretation and authorship in its own right. For, as we’ve established, if James Baldwin didn’t speak these words, who did? Whose voice is it? Where is it coming from? I believe that Glaude was too quick to dismiss Baldwin’s appeal “as an avatar of supposed seriousness,” and I argue that Twitter users engage in collective acts of authorship under the auspices of Baldwin as a single literary avatar, creating a communal literary mythology based on Baldwin’s real life and words but also extending beyond him. I call these changes, omissions, and manipulations of Baldwin’s words “re-authorship” as opposed to “misquotation,” in order to emphasize the generative creative process at work here as opposed to insinuating only error and inaccuracy.</p> <p>This quote and its many “re-authorships” reveal what the #BlackLivesMatter movement values about Baldwin and the different, sometimes competing ways that Baldwin is being used politically (for of course the #BlackLivesMatter movement is not a monolithic one).</p> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Baldwin. Rage. <a href="http://t.co/CsBuw2Xhws">pic.twitter.com/CsBuw2Xhws</a></p>&mdash; deray mckesson (@deray) <a href="https://twitter.com/deray/status/585663284138901504">April 8, 2015</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Baldwin. Rage. (via <a href="https://twitter.com/JIJennings">@JIJennings</a>) <a href="http://t.co/QUvrjrJC32">pic.twitter.com/QUvrjrJC32</a></p>&mdash; deray mckesson (@deray) <a href="https://twitter.com/deray/status/611853727943671808">June 19, 2015</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <p>First, these “re-authorships” reveal an appreciation for Baldwin’s relevance and perceived prescience, that he seems like he’s clairvoyantly speaking to our contemporary moment. The most popular, “re-authored” versions of this quote update Baldwin’s language to match contemporary racial discourse and thus enhance Baldwin’s perceived prescience to the point of its erasure, collapsing the historical distance between Baldwin and the present moment. By replacing “To be a Negro” with “To be Black,” these Twitter users ditch an antiquated word that would otherwise un-hiply announce Baldwin’s historical distance and discord. They transform him from a past prophet into a present living ally and member of the movement, who speaks in the contemporary moment in the language of the contemporary moment.</p> <p>Second, these readers champion Baldwin’s intellectuality and systemic understanding of history and identity, even while they dispense with some of the characteristic prose style that allowed Baldwin to complexly explore and elucidate these subjects during his career—his penchant for careful qualifiers, multiple clauses, and general long-windedness. These Twitter users extract what they take to be the essential conceptual nuggets and craft them into a more concise and confident, 140-character abiding style. Baldwin’s second infinitive and qualifier—“to be a Negro and <em>to be relatively conscious</em>”—gets lopped off and transformed into a single compact identity—“to be Black and conscious.” This powerful, rearranged phrase echoes one of the #BlackLivesMatter movement’s persistent calls, to “stay woke,” a slang phrase that means to be “awake” or “conscious” of systemic racism and injustice, a phrase that gained traction on Black Twitter and has been strongly taken up as a rallying cry of the #BlackLivesMatter movement especially since Ferguson. These Twitter re-authorships thus make Baldwin into a sort of literary antecedent of “wokeness.” The explicit naming of “America” also demonstrates an appreciation for Baldwin’s understanding of the particularities of American history, which they enhance by naming it and pinning it down.</p> <p>Third, and perhaps most important, these readers clearly invoke Baldwin’s rage. Tellingly, what remains the same throughout every single evolution of this quote is the word rage. This is not loving Baldwin, who we see invoked elsewhere in the archive:</p> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;This fight begins in the heart&quot;: <a href="https://twitter.com/LailaLalami">@LailaLalami</a> on reading James Baldwin as Ferguson seethes: <a href="http://t.co/pwErhUga3Z">http://t.co/pwErhUga3Z</a></p>&mdash; NPR Books (@nprbooks) <a href="https://twitter.com/nprbooks/status/501866250973478912">August 19, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Love takes off the masks that we fear we cannot live without and know we cannot live within. + <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/jamesbaldwin?src=hash">#jamesbaldwin</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/NMOS14?src=hash">#NMOS14</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; Mihee Kim-Kort (@miheekimkort) <a href="https://twitter.com/miheekimkort/status/500618364524691456">August 16, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Bill T. Jones <a href="https://twitter.com/NewYorkLiveArts">@NewYorkLiveArts</a>: James Baldwin loved America. He just wanted it to make good on its promises <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a> <a href="http://t.co/MVMmMOSeNC">http://t.co/MVMmMOSeNC</a></p>&mdash; CBCSundayEdition (@CBCSunday) <a href="https://twitter.com/CBCSunday/status/538880647930994688">November 30, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <p>This is angry Baldwin. By manipulating the sentence’s conclusion from the more open-ended and cautious “in a rage almost all the time” to the more permanent, climactic “constant state of rage,” these readers place special emphasis on “rage.” And this is where I think Baldwin’s literary and intellectual mythos most comes into play, the reason Twitter users respond to this quote in particular and why they retain his attribution even when they change his words.</p> <p>Because the collective outrage over Michael Brown’s shooting and Darren Wilson’s non-indictment—and the protests happening in the streets across the country—was being dismissed and criminalized as “rioting” and “thuggish,” as unwarranted and overblown. These Twitter users are thus historicizing, legitimizing, and giving license to their own rage by invoking it through Baldwin, an eloquent, elite artist recognized by the establishment. This is not the anger of rioting thugs; this is the anger of an articulate, textually-deft, and conscious movement. One Twitter user expressed frustration about the movement’s gravitation toward James Baldwin as model and muse, pointing out the potential dissonance between the language and experiences of James Baldwin and that of everyday black teenagers in Ferguson:</p> <p>[Tweet deleted]</p> <p>But this tweet reveals that that’s precisely why Baldwin is being invoked and mythologized, as a pronouncement that this movement cannot be reduced only to felons with bad credit, as a way of pulling Baldwin closer to West Florissant. In short, I believe these tweets represent a complex, collective reader response, an affiliation that is being built through and around an established literary figure. Perhaps most crucially, this literary network is <em>not</em> happening in a university classroom or at an academic conference, but rather it’s happening organically on Twitter, and I think literary scholars should be paying attention.</p> <p><b></b></p> <hr/> <p><b></b></p> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote"> <p>Lev Manovich, <a href="http://culturalanalytics.org/2016/05/the-science-of-culture-social-computing-digital-humanities-and-cultural-analytics/">“The Science of Culture? Social Computing, Digital Humanities and Cultural Analytics”</a> <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote"> <p>These <a href="https://archive.org/details/ferguson-tweet-ids">openly available archives</a> were collected by Ed Summers, Molly Loyd, Gregory Coleman, Kimberly Lamke, and Benjamin Sugar, and this project is indebted to their foresight in collecting these tweets and their intellectual generosity in sharing them. Twitter’s Terms of Service does not allow bulk distribution of Twitter data, but it does allow the distribution of tweet “ids,” unique identifiers assigned to every tweet which can be used to retroactively access the full tweet metadata from the Twitter API using a tool like twarc, which was also created by Ed Summers. This process is called “hydrating.” Because “hydrating” these tweets comes after the fact, however, any tweet that has been deleted between the time of its original publication and the time of hydration disappears entirely. From the 13,480,000 ids in the first collection, I was able to “hydrate” 10,441,785 tweets, a process that took approximately 8 days (since the Twitter’s API rate limit only allows requests for up to 72,000 tweets per hour). From the 15,080,078 ids in the second collection, I was able to “hydrate” 7,868,540 tweets, which reveals a surprising number of missing/deleted tweets that I would like to more fully theorize and speculate about in the future. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote"> <p>For more on how I used twarc and hydration, see <a href="http://melaniewalsh.org/2016/11/05/building-tweets-of-a-native-son-part1.html">“Part 1: Building the ‘Tweets of a Native Son’ Archive (twarc and twarc-report)”</a> <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote"> <p>For more on how I reshaped the JSON data, see <a href="http://melaniewalsh.org/2016/11/07/building-tweets-of-a-native-son-part2.html">“Part 2: Building the ‘Tweets of a Native Son’ Archive (jq and regular expressions)”</a> <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="twitter"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The following is a transcript from my paper “Tweets of a Native Son: The Mythology of James Baldwin on Twitter,” which I gave at the MMLA conference on November 12. Huge thanks to Doug Knox from the HDW for helping me figure out how to wrangle Twitter data and to Ed Summers from MITH for generously sharing data, tools, and thoughtfulness.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Part 2: Building the “Tweets of a Native Son” Archive (jq and regular expressions)</title><link href="https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2016/building-tweets-of-a-native-son-part2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Part 2: Building the “Tweets of a Native Son” Archive (jq and regular expressions)"/><published>2016-11-07T21:53:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-11-07T21:53:00+00:00</updated><id>https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2016/building-tweets-of-a-native-son-part2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2016/building-tweets-of-a-native-son-part2/"><![CDATA[<p>In <a href="http://melaniewalsh.org/2016/11/05/building-tweets-of-a-native-son-part1.html">Part 1</a>, I explained how I “hydrated” 17 million tweets that mentioned “Ferguson” from August and November 2014 by using <a href="https://github.com/DocNow/twarc">twarc</a> and how I generated summaries for these collections (# of tweets and users, top hashtags, top URLs, top image URLS, etc.) using <a href="https://github.com/pbinkley/twarc-report">twarc-report</a>. But how and where does James Baldwin fit into the picture?</p> <p>In this post, I’m going to talk about what Twitter metadata looks like (spoiler alert: it’s pretty kooky) and how I reshaped the metadata to find only tweets that mentioned James Baldwin by using <a href="https://stedolan.github.io/jq/">jq</a>, a command-line utility for filtering JSON data.</p> <hr/> <p><b></b></p> <p>Twitter metadata is wild. Every single tweet carries with it an enormous amount of information. Even a tweet as seemingly meaningless as “:poop:” carries with it not just the “text” (:poop:) of the tweet but also many other metadata fields such as:</p> <ul> <li>when the tweet was created</li> <li>how many times the tweet has been favorited or retweeted</li> <li>what language the tweet was written in</li> <li>which user wrote the tweet</li> <li>when the user created his or her account</li> <li>the user’s profile description and profile picture and profile background color</li> <li>the user’s location</li> <li>how many people follow the user</li> <li>how many people the user follows</li> <li>how many tweets the user has ever favorited</li> <li>how many tweets the user has ever sent</li> </ul> <p>…and much, much more.<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p> <p>Here’s just a glimpse of a single tweet from the August archive, which goes on for 96 lines:</p> <p><img src="../../../assets/img/json1.jpg" alt="alt text"/></p> <p>As a tweet gets more complex—a reply to another user with a hashtag and a URL or a retweet with an image—the metadata gets even bigger and richer.</p> <p>This richness makes the metadata wonderful for research purposes, allowing us to investigate all kinds of questions, but it also makes the data difficult to work with. If we want to extract just the tweets that mention James Baldwin, the nested structure of the JSON data (which you can learn more about <a href="http://www.json.org/">here</a>) makes that a tricky task.</p> <p>This is where <a href="https://stedolan.github.io/jq/">jq</a> comes in, a command-line utility for reshaping JSON data. With jq, you can extract information from particular fields (“text,” “coordinates,” retweet_count,” etc.) even when those fields are nested within other fields. You can even output the JSON data to a flat CSV file.<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> For my purposes, I extracted only the tweets that mentioned James Baldwin by performing the filter operation <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">select()</code> on the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.text</code> field of the tweets, combined with a regular expressions string match for “James Baldwin” <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">test("James Baldwin")</code>:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>jq -c "select(.text | test(\"James Baldwin\"))" tweets.json &gt; jamesbaldwin.json
</code></pre></div></div> <p>This operation returned 1,697 tweets that mentioned “James Baldwin” from the August Ferguson tweet collection. But that’s only when “James Baldwin” was spelled correctly with proper capitalization and spacing. So I decided to expand the search to collect other variations of his name without regard for capitalization and spacing, as well as permitting just a first initial and even misspellings that may have accidentally dropped the “d” from his name (#JamesBaldwin; J BALDWIN; james baldwin, James Balwin, etc.) :</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>jq -c "select(.text | test(\"J(ames|) ?Bald?win\";\"i\"))" tweets.json &gt; jamesbaldwin.json
</code></pre></div></div> <p>This operation returned an increased <strong><big>1,839</big></strong> tweets from the August collection and <strong><big>1,393</big></strong> tweets from the November collection. I experimented with an even more expansive search for simply “Baldwin,” which returned 3,410 tweets, but too many of them referenced a “Baldwin” not related to the literary James of interest, picking up instead on users’ last names, the actor Alec Baldwin, etc.</p> <p>These <strong><big>3,232</big></strong> tweets from August and November quantitatively confirm scholars’ claims—among them, Eddie S. Glaude and William J. Maxwell—that Baldwin is and was a leading literary voice in the burgeoning #BlackLivesMatter movement, since it proves that James Baldwin was being invoked and talked about on Twitter in the aftermath of Ferguson.</p> <p>Yet the James Baldwin conversation represents less than <strong>one-percent</strong> of the total Twitter conversation in either dataset, which serves as a tempering reminder that the scholarly sense of what is dominant in the larger cultural conversation may be skewed by scholarly newsfeeds. These numbers may even seem small enough to dismiss the case for Baldwin’s prominence on Twitter. But when cross-compared to other prominent black writers, Baldwin is far and away the most invoked. The words “James Baldwin” appear more in the August collection than “Claudia Rankine” (416), “Langston Hughes” (281), “Assata Shakur” (130), “Ta-Nehisi Coates” (129), “Toni Morrison” (72), “Teju Cole” (55), “Richard Wright” (50), “Ralph Ellison” (49), and “Amiri Baraka” (10) combined.</p> <p>But why? Why does Baldwin appear so much more frequently than other black writers? What about his style, insights, or legacy resonates in this particular historical moment and on this particular platform?</p> <p>These are the literary questions that I will seek to answer in future posts through close-reading and further investigation of the data. But for now, I’ll just share an overview of the Ferguson-Baldwin data produced using some twarc utilities and twarc-report. Check out the most popular retweets, hashtags, URLs, and image URLs below.</p> <h1 id="august-baldwin-tweet-archive"><strong>August Baldwin Tweet Archive</strong></h1> <hr/> <table> <thead> <tr> <th> </th> <th> </th> <th> </th> <th> </th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td><strong>Tweets</strong>:</td> <td>1,839</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Users</strong>:</td> <td>1,753</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Has Hashtag</strong>:</td> <td>1,169 (63.57%)</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Hashtags</strong>:</td> <td>115</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Has URL</strong>:</td> <td>609 (33.12%)</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>URLs</strong>:</td> <td>166</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Has Image URL</strong>:</td> <td>47 (2.56%)</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Image URLs</strong>:</td> <td>18</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Retweets</strong>:</td> <td>1,327 (72.16%)</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Geo</strong>:</td> <td>11 (0.60%)</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Earliest Tweet</strong>: 2014-08-11 04:16:44 UTC</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;To be a Negro in this country and to be relatively conscious is to be in a rage almost all the time. ” ― James Baldwin <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; Renaissance Man (@cjfluker) <a href="https://twitter.com/cjfluker/status/498684414483001344">August 11, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Latest Tweet</strong>:</td> <td>2014-08-27 12:46:48 UTC</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&#39;This Fight Begins In The Heart&#39;: Reading James Baldwin As Ferguson Seethes : NPR <a href="http://t.co/iLyNSrgwFZ">http://t.co/iLyNSrgwFZ</a></p>&mdash; AC De Lion (@anydel) <a href="https://twitter.com/anydel/status/504610983055081472">August 27, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td><strong>Total Duration</strong>:</td> <td>16 days, 8:30:04</td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p><strong>Top 10 Retweets:</strong></p> <p><b></b></p> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;To be Black and conscious in America is to be in a constant state of rage.&quot; - James Baldwin <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; zellie (@zellieimani) <a href="https://twitter.com/zellieimani/status/499871572023586816">August 14, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;To be a Negro in this country and to be relatively conscious is to be in a rage almost all the time.&quot; —James Baldwin <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; Crystal Kayiza (@c_kayiza) <a href="https://twitter.com/c_kayiza/status/498832276667793408">August 11, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">My new article on <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/MikeBrown?src=hash">#MikeBrown</a>, systemic racism and James Baldwin; if of interest, please share.<a href="http://t.co/DxhX3gCnnF">http://t.co/DxhX3gCnnF</a></p>&mdash; Musa Okwonga (@Okwonga) <a href="https://twitter.com/Okwonga/status/500008972016156672">August 14, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">if you&#39;re following <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a>, watch this essential <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/JamesBaldwin?src=hash">#JamesBaldwin</a> testimony in June 1963: <a href="https://t.co/EVTTXgp82s">https://t.co/EVTTXgp82s</a></p>&mdash; Jose Antonio Vargas (@joseiswriting) <a href="https://twitter.com/joseiswriting/status/501231389333667842">August 18, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;This fight begins in the heart&quot;: <a href="https://twitter.com/LailaLalami">@LailaLalami</a> on reading James Baldwin as Ferguson seethes: <a href="http://t.co/pwErhUga3Z">http://t.co/pwErhUga3Z</a></p>&mdash; NPR Books (@nprbooks) <a href="https://twitter.com/nprbooks/status/501866250973478912">August 19, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">‘Not everything that is faced can be changed, but nothing can be changed until it is faced.’ - James Baldwin <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/FERGUSON?src=hash">#FERGUSON</a></p>&mdash; sandrine. (@drineee) <a href="https://twitter.com/drineee/status/503726050258325505">August 25, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr"><a href="http://t.co/mFvaZuMAIw">http://t.co/mFvaZuMAIw</a> Teju Cole&#39;s beautiful &amp; lacerating piece on James Baldwin, the &quot;black body&quot; &amp; the white gaze, <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a> &amp; beyond.</p>&mdash; Joyce Carol Oates (@JoyceCarolOates) <a href="https://twitter.com/JoyceCarolOates/status/503278563056156673">August 23, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">A quote from James Baldwin in a PSA on <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a> that aired during last night’s <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/VMAs?src=hash">#VMAs</a> WATCH: <a href="http://t.co/X0Q7Zs2z3y">http://t.co/X0Q7Zs2z3y</a> <a href="http://t.co/VyMthSXw6c">pic.twitter.com/VyMthSXw6c</a></p>&mdash; SPLC (@splcenter) <a href="https://twitter.com/splcenter/status/503947612299755520">August 25, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;But black people raise their children as a rehearsal for danger.” -James Baldwin <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; Salamishah Tillet (@salamishah) <a href="https://twitter.com/salamishah/status/502105003033894912">August 20, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;White people think that childhood is a rehearsal for success. White people think of themselves as safe.&quot; -James Baldwin <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; Salamishah Tillet (@salamishah) <a href="https://twitter.com/salamishah/status/502104900164386816">August 20, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <p><br/></p> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td><strong>Top Hashtags:</strong></td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>1. ferguson</td> <td>1,093</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>2. jamesbaldwin</td> <td>122</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>3. vmas</td> <td>84</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>4. lookdifferent</td> <td>61</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>5. mikebrown</td> <td>53</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>6. nmos14</td> <td>28</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>7. vmawards</td> <td>17</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>8. books</td> <td>15</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>9. vmas2014</td> <td>15</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>10. moralmonday</td> <td>15</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Top URLs:</strong></td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>1. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kXwVnYGJ_Cw">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kXwVnYGJ_Cw</a></td> <td>73</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>2. <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/books/page-turner/black-body-re-reading-james-baldwins-stranger-village">http://www.newyorker.com/books/page-turner/black-body-re-reading-james-baldwins-stranger-village</a></td> <td>61</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>3. <a href="http://n.pr/1lfM1Ej">http://n.pr/1lfM1Ej</a></td> <td>59</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>4. <a href="http://sp.lc/VOarbH">http://sp.lc/VOarbH</a></td> <td>49</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>5. <a href="http://n.pr/1rstgvg">http://n.pr/1rstgvg</a></td> <td>33</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>6. <a href="http://wp.me/p4Rl2x-aCX">http://wp.me/p4Rl2x-aCX</a></td> <td>27</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>7. <a href="http://esqm.ag/6015W6MW">http://esqm.ag/6015W6MW</a></td> <td>23</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>8. <a href="https://twitter.com/drgoddess/status/503726211621982208">https://twitter.com/drgoddess/status/503726211621982208</a></td> <td>15</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>9. <a href="http://j.mp/1p3a2t0">http://j.mp/1p3a2t0</a></td> <td>15</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>10. <a href="http://n.pr/VFtghp">http://n.pr/VFtghp</a></td> <td>11</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Top Image URLs</strong>:</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>1. <a href="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/Bv5Mng5CIAAdKqx.jpg"><img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/Bv5Mng5CIAAdKqx.jpg" alt="alt text"/></a></td> <td>15</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>2. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/Bv2YYDuIgAIrMx1.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>6</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>3. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/BvSVjOhCYAAp4HO.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>5</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>4. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/BvsNlfPCAAEE-4I.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>4</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>5. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/BvdepJJCIAASmnF.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>2</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>6. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/BvfXPJ6CMAET-7x.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>2</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>7. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/Bv5hrs5IAAEJ-j9.png" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>2</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>8. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/Bu_9kkZIgAAQr4J.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>1</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>9. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/BvVH43QIQAA80d-.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>1</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>10. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/BvVgszMIgAAsEUz.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>1</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p><br/></p> <h1 id="november-baldwin-archive"><strong>November Baldwin Archive</strong></h1> <hr/> <table> <thead> <tr> <th> </th> <th> </th> <th> </th> <th> </th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td><strong>Tweets</strong>:</td> <td>1,393</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Users</strong>:</td> <td>1,231</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Has Hashtag</strong>:</td> <td>952 (68.34%)</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Hashtags</strong>:</td> <td>113</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Has URL</strong>:</td> <td>388 (27.85%)</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>URLs</strong>:</td> <td>203</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Has Image URL</strong>:</td> <td>213 (15.29%)</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Image URLs</strong>:</td> <td>47</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Retweets</strong>:</td> <td>987 (70.85%)</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Geo</strong>:</td> <td>11 (0.79%)</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Earliest Tweet</strong>:</td> <td>2014-11-12 05:38:56 UTC</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;It is certain, in any case, that ignorance, allied with power, is the most ferocious enemy justice can have.&quot; ~ James Baldwin~ || <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; Dante Boykin (@DanteB4u) <a href="https://twitter.com/DanteB4u/status/532407171867480064">November 12, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Latest Tweet (Retweet)</strong>:</td> <td>2014-12-10 04:08:08 UTC</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;If I love you, I have to make you conscious of the things you do not see.&quot; James Baldwin <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/icantbreathe?src=hash">#icantbreathe</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ferguson?src=hash">#ferguson</a> <a href="https://t.co/OKyGqNu5HX">https://t.co/OKyGqNu5HX</a></p>&mdash; Laurenellen McCann!! (@elle_mccann) <a href="https://twitter.com/elle_mccann/status/542393298833256449">December 9, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td><strong>Total Duration</strong>:</td> <td>27 days, 22:29:12</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p><b></b></p> <p><strong>Top 10 Retweets:</strong></p> <p><b></b></p> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">James Baldwin quoted for Mike Brown. Union Square <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a> demo <a href="http://t.co/u23WRicZR8">pic.twitter.com/u23WRicZR8</a></p>&mdash; Molly Crabapple (@mollycrabapple) <a href="https://twitter.com/mollycrabapple/status/537045590300188672">November 25, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;To be black in America is to be in a constant state of rage.&quot;<br/><br/>-James Baldwin <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/MikeBrown?src=hash">#MikeBrown</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/FergusonTheRoot?src=hash">#FergusonTheRoot</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; Courtney Thornton (@courteroy_) <a href="https://twitter.com/courteroy_/status/537077232599330816">November 25, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">We live in &quot;a civilization which has always glorified violence--unless the Negro had the gun.&quot;--James Baldwin circa 1963 <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; Jose Antonio Vargas (@joseiswriting) <a href="https://twitter.com/joseiswriting/status/537136943318831105">November 25, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;To be black and conscious in america is a constant state of rage&quot; - James Baldwin<a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/noblackjusticenoblackfriday?src=hash">#noblackjusticenoblackfriday</a><a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; Gbenga Akinnagbe (@GbengaAkinnagbe) <a href="https://twitter.com/GbengaAkinnagbe/status/537130288787517442">November 25, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">My article on <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/MikeBrown?src=hash">#MikeBrown</a>, with an important quote from James Baldwin. If of interest, please share. <a href="http://t.co/S5DsNyJAmG">http://t.co/S5DsNyJAmG</a></p>&mdash; Musa Okwonga (@Okwonga) <a href="https://twitter.com/Okwonga/status/537188928923918336">November 25, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">James Baldwin&#39;s prophetic words in 1960<a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/BlackLivesMatter?src=hash">#BlackLivesMatter</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/FergusionDecision?src=hash">#FergusionDecision</a> <a href="http://t.co/G4KX6bRdfF">pic.twitter.com/G4KX6bRdfF</a></p>&mdash; Rahiel Tesfamariam (@RahielT) <a href="https://twitter.com/RahielT/status/537122331597225984">November 25, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;To be a Negro in this country and to be relatively conscious is to be in a rage almost all the time.&quot; —James Baldwin <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; Crystal Kayiza (@c_kayiza) <a href="https://twitter.com/c_kayiza/status/498832276667793408">August 11, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">James Baldwin: &quot;The law is meant to be my servant and not my master, still less my torturer and my murderer.&quot; <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; Nikhil Goyal (@nikhilgoya_l) <a href="https://twitter.com/nikhilgoya_l/status/537071543579594753">November 25, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">“To be a Negro in this country and to be relatively conscious is to be in a rage almost all the time. ” – James Baldwin <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; Yasiel Plug (@Ketchcast) <a href="https://twitter.com/Ketchcast/status/537074466262507520">November 25, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;To be a Negro in this country and to be relatively conscious is to be in a rage almost all the time.&quot; - James Baldwin <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; BlackHistoryStudies (@BlkHistStudies) <a href="https://twitter.com/BlkHistStudies/status/538014453934333952">November 27, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <p><b></b></p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th> </th> <th> </th> <th> </th> <th> </th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Top Hashtags</strong>:</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>1. ferguson</td> <td>836</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>2. mikebrown</td> <td>196</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>3. blacklivesmatter</td> <td>174</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>4. jamesbaldwin</td> <td>104</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>5. noblackjusticenoblackfriday</td> <td>48</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>6. fergusiondecision</td> <td>45</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>7. icantbreathe</td> <td>34</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>8. fergusontheroot</td> <td>23</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>9. hiphoped</td> <td>22</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>10. standup</td> <td>20</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Top URLs</strong>:</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>1. <a href="http://Advocate.com">http://Advocate.com</a></td> <td>54</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>2. <a href="http://www.cbc.ca/thesundayedition/features/2014/11/30/post-11/">http://www.cbc.ca/thesundayedition/features/2014/11/30/post-11/</a></td> <td>33</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>3. <a href="http://esqm.ag/6013t1KF">http://esqm.ag/6013t1KF</a></td> <td>23</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>4. <a href="http://shar.es/1XEN2s">http://shar.es/1XEN2s</a></td> <td>18</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>5. <a href="http://www.advocate.com/politics/2014/11/25/5-james-baldwin-quotes-foreshadowed-ferguson">http://www.advocate.com/politics/2014/11/25/5-james-baldwin-quotes-foreshadowed-ferguson</a></td> <td>18</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>6. <a href="http://www.agos.com.tr/tr/yazi/9893/fergusondan-yuksekovaya-james-baldwinin-ruhuyla">http://www.agos.com.tr/tr/yazi/9893/fergusondan-yuksekovaya-james-baldwinin-ruhuyla</a></td> <td>16</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>7. <a href="http://www.neontommy.com/news/2014/12/ferguson-and-blacklivesmatter-illustrate-how-james-baldwin-s-words-continue-resonate-mo">http://www.neontommy.com/news/2014/12/ferguson-and-blacklivesmatter-illustrate-how-james-baldwin-s-words-continue-resonate-mo</a></td> <td>11</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>8. <a href="http://bit.ly/1yTCKna">http://bit.ly/1yTCKna</a></td> <td>11</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>9. <a href="http://bit.ly/1B9TCdI">http://bit.ly/1B9TCdI</a></td> <td>10</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>10. <a href="http://www.newstatesman.com/politics/2014/08/amid-tear-gas-and-arrests-reporters-ferguson-we-must-not-lose-sight-mike-brown">http://www.newstatesman.com/politics/2014/08/amid-tear-gas-and-arrests-reporters-ferguson-we-must-not-lose-sight-mike-brown</a></td> <td>9</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Top Image URLs</strong>:</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>1. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/B3P4HZ-IQAAVvS1.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>45</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>2. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/B3Q96NpIMAAnv04.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>44</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>3. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/B3UWme1IIAItKda.png" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>23</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>4. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/B4L2sPYCQAIJlSO.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>19</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>5. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/B4auO9rCAAA_f_m.png" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>9</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>6. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/B3jBSQHCQAAY8ek.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>8</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>7. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/B3T5Iy-CYAEZ_Gi.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>7</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>8. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/B4audKGCAAAT34u.png" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>5</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>9. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/B3Zjf4GCEAA_eTx.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>4</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>10. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/B3esOS8IIAAlLbS.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>4</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote"> <p>If you’re interested in finding out more about the structure of Twitter metadata, check out <a href="https://dev.twitter.com/overview/api/tweets">Twitter’s documentation here</a>. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote"> <p>For a full jq tutorial, I recommend Matthew Lincoln’s very helpful <a href="http://programminghistorian.org/lessons/json-and-jq">“Reshaping JSON with jq”</a>. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="twitter"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In Part 1, I explained how I “hydrated” 17 million tweets that mentioned “Ferguson” from August and November 2014 by using twarc and how I generated summaries for these collections (# of tweets and users, top hashtags, top URLs, top image URLS, etc.) using twarc-report. But how and where does James Baldwin fit into the picture?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Part 1: Building the “Tweets of a Native Son” Archive (twarc and twarc-report)</title><link href="https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2016/building-tweets-of-a-native-son-part1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Part 1: Building the “Tweets of a Native Son” Archive (twarc and twarc-report)"/><published>2016-11-05T23:56:56+00:00</published><updated>2016-11-05T23:56:56+00:00</updated><id>https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2016/building-tweets-of-a-native-son-part1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2016/building-tweets-of-a-native-son-part1/"><![CDATA[<p>So my project “Tweets of a Native Son” examines the way that Twitter conversations about Ferguson and the #BlackLivesMater movement invoke the literary author James Baldwin. What’s my archive? How did I build it?</p> <p>Tweets can be ephemeral little stinkers. Since Twitter’s Search API only allows you to collect tweets from the last 1-2 weeks, foresight is huge when building a Twitter archive. Thankfully, Ed Summers had the foresight to start collecting tweets that mentioned “Ferguson” (upper or lowercase; with or without hashtag) in the weeks and months following Michael Brown’s shooting and, just as important, the generosity to share them <a href="https://archive.org/details/ferguson-tweet-ids">openly</a>. Though Twitter’s Terms of Service does not allow bulk distribution of Twitter data, it does allow the distribution of tweet “ids,” which are unique identifiers that get assigned to every tweet and can be used to retroactively access the full tweet metadata, a process called “hydrating” that can be performed with a command line Python tool like <a href="https://github.com/DocNow/twarc">twarc</a>, which was also created by Ed Summers. Yeah, Ed rules.</p> <p>So the first step in building my Baldwin Tweet archive was hydrating the Ferguson tweet collections from both August and November, which you can perform by running the command <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">twarc.py --hydrate</code>:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>mwalsh@ada:~/ferguson-tweet-ids/data$ gunzip ids.txt.gz
mwalsh@ada:~/ferguson-tweet-ids/data$ nohup twarc.py --hydrate ids.txt &gt; tweets.json &amp;
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Since Twitter’s API rate limit only allows requests for up to 72,000 tweets per hour, this process took approximately 8 and 9 days, respectively. The utility <a href="https://github.com/pbinkley/twarc-report">“twarc-report,”</a> created by Peter Binkley, allows me to generate a helpful, summarizing overview of these collections (# of tweets and users, top hashtags, top URLs, top images, etc.), which you can perform by running <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">reportprofile.py</code> with the flag <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-o text</code>:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>mwalsh@ada:~/ferguson-tweet-ids/data$ ~/twarc-report/reportprofile.py -o text tweets.json
mwalsh@ada:~/ferguson-indictment-tweet-ids/data$ ~/twarc-report/reportprofile.py -o text tweets.indictment.json
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Here’s (some of) what the report spits out…</p> <h1 id="august-ferguson-tweet-collection"><strong>August Ferguson Tweet Collection</strong></h1> <hr/> <table> <thead> <tr> <th> </th> <th> </th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td><strong>Tweets:</strong></td> <td>10,441,785</td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Users:</strong></td> <td>1,596,104</td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Has Hashtag:</strong></td> <td>6,898,701 (66.07%)</td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Hashtags:</strong></td> <td>99,695</td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Has URL:</strong></td> <td>3,317,445 (31.77%)</td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>URLs:</strong></td> <td>664,691</td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Has Image URL:</strong></td> <td>1,593,403 (15.26%)</td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Image URLs:</strong></td> <td>134,431</td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Retweets:</strong></td> <td>7,411,799 (70.98%)</td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Geo:</strong></td> <td>74,678 (0.72%)</td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Earliest Tweet:</strong></td> <td>2014-08-10 22:44:33 UTC</td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Latest Tweet:</strong></td> <td>2014-08-27 15:15:50 UTC</td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Total Duration:</strong></td> <td>16 days, 16:31:07</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <table> <thead> <tr> <th> </th> <th> </th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td><strong>Top Hashtags:</strong></td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>1. ferguson</td> <td>6,422,131</td> </tr> <tr> <td>2. mikebrown</td> <td>583,141</td> </tr> <tr> <td>3. michaelbrown</td> <td>158,552</td> </tr> <tr> <td>4. justiceformikebrown</td> <td>84,061</td> </tr> <tr> <td>5. tcot</td> <td>70,702</td> </tr> <tr> <td>6. gaza</td> <td>70,338</td> </tr> <tr> <td>7. stl</td> <td>58,662</td> </tr> <tr> <td>8. handsupdontshoot</td> <td>47,126</td> </tr> <tr> <td>9. darrenwilson</td> <td>40,091</td> </tr> <tr> <td>10. fergusonshooting</td> <td>31,643</td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Top URLs:</strong></td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>1. <a href="http://new.livestream.com/accounts/9035483/events/3271930">http://new.livestream.com/accounts/9035483/events/3271930</a></td> <td>37,917</td> </tr> <tr> <td>2. <a href="http://bzfd.it/VDlPH8">http://bzfd.it/VDlPH8</a></td> <td>12,906</td> </tr> <tr> <td>3. <a href="http://thebea.st/1l8uDRK">http://thebea.st/1l8uDRK</a></td> <td>10,773</td> </tr> <tr> <td>4. <a href="http://bbc.in/1uS3tSd">http://bbc.in/1uS3tSd</a></td> <td>9,841</td> </tr> <tr> <td>5. <a href="http://www.livestream.com/activistworldnewsnow">http://www.livestream.com/activistworldnewsnow</a></td> <td>8,276</td> </tr> <tr> <td>6. <a href="http://wapo.st/1sXk4Sj">http://wapo.st/1sXk4Sj</a></td> <td>7,535</td> </tr> <tr> <td>7. <a href="http://es.pn/1AvncY9">http://es.pn/1AvncY9</a></td> <td>7,514</td> </tr> <tr> <td>8. <a href="https://vine.co/v/M3rWtqnrHi9">https://vine.co/v/M3rWtqnrHi9</a></td> <td>6,771</td> </tr> <tr> <td>9. <a href="http://ind.pn/1qjd6lO">http://ind.pn/1qjd6lO</a></td> <td>6,366</td> </tr> <tr> <td>10. <a href="http://ow.ly/ADgCF">http://ow.ly/ADgCF</a></td> <td>5,909</td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Top Image URLs:</strong></td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>1. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/BvSVYWKIIAAGPhB.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>21,899</td> </tr> <tr> <td>2. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/BvROlxsIUAA632n.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>10,486</td> </tr> <tr> <td>3. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/BvUSCd4CMAEiZ-u.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>10,319</td> </tr> <tr> <td>4. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/BvSlV60CUAAEPhU.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>9,029</td> </tr> <tr> <td>5. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/BvaPNHTIIAE6UIi.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>7,956</td> </tr> <tr> <td>6. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/BvYUwzIIMAAiH62.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>7,586</td> </tr> <tr> <td>7. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/Bu9zJKeIIAAa4Jt.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>6,842</td> </tr> <tr> <td>8. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/Bu9bSPRCIAAnntQ.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>6,223</td> </tr> <tr> <td>9. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/Bu-lkolCAAIwyN0.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>5,998</td> </tr> <tr> <td>10. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/Buu2CQGIUAEqJPU.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>5,195</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p><br/></p> <h1 id="november-ferguson-tweet-collection"><strong>November Ferguson Tweet Collection</strong></h1> <hr/> <table> <thead> <tr> <th> </th> <th> </th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td><strong>Tweets:</strong></td> <td>7,868,540</td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Users:</strong></td> <td>1,761,950</td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Has Hashtag:</strong></td> <td>4,567,256 (58.04%)</td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Hashtags:</strong></td> <td>110,097</td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Has URL:</strong></td> <td>3,514,869 (44.67%)</td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>URLs:</strong></td> <td>927,040</td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Has Image URL:</strong></td> <td>1,465,857 (18.63%)</td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Image URLs:</strong></td> <td>191,684</td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Retweets:</strong></td> <td>5,004,081 (63.60%)</td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Geo:</strong></td> <td>51,007 (0.65%)</td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Earliest Tweet:</strong></td> <td>2014-11-11 22:17:06 UTC</td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Latest Tweet:</strong></td> <td>2014-12-10 05:15:31 UTC</td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Total Duration:</strong></td> <td>28 days, 6:58:25</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <table> <thead> <tr> <th> </th> <th> </th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td><strong>Top Hashtags:</strong></td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>1. ferguson</td> <td>3,969,513</td> </tr> <tr> <td>2. mikebrown</td> <td>188,976</td> </tr> <tr> <td>3. ericgarner</td> <td>178,139</td> </tr> <tr> <td>4. <a name="blm"><span style="color: red"><a href="#bld"><strong>blacklivesmatter</strong></a></span></a></td> <td><strong>151,749</strong></td> </tr> <tr> <td>5. fergusondecision</td> <td>118,405</td> </tr> <tr> <td>6. michaelbrown</td> <td>105,607</td> </tr> <tr> <td>7. tcot</td> <td>99,477</td> </tr> <tr> <td>8. darrenwilson</td> <td>89,154</td> </tr> <tr> <td>9. icantbreathe</td> <td>89,000</td> </tr> <tr> <td>10. shutitdown</td> <td>45,296</td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Top URLs:</strong></td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>1. <a href="http://cnn.it/1tAZkMJ">http://cnn.it/1tAZkMJ</a></td> <td>11,592</td> </tr> <tr> <td>2. <a href="http://nbcnews.to/12fXQ5f">http://nbcnews.to/12fXQ5f</a></td> <td>10,644</td> </tr> <tr> <td>3. <a href="http://ble.ac/1B376rD">http://ble.ac/1B376rD</a></td> <td>9,848</td> </tr> <tr> <td>4. <a href="http://invst.rs/7f2xJB">http://invst.rs/7f2xJB</a></td> <td>8,609</td> </tr> <tr> <td>5. <a href="http://nyp.st/1vjOX47">http://nyp.st/1vjOX47</a></td> <td>8,535</td> </tr> <tr> <td>6. <a href="http://cbsn.ws/1vzqR5B">http://cbsn.ws/1vzqR5B</a></td> <td>8,097</td> </tr> <tr> <td>7. <a href="http://bit.ly/1d5qTtO">http://bit.ly/1d5qTtO</a></td> <td>7,460</td> </tr> <tr> <td>8. <a href="http://vine.co/v/On1x6iUuwxK">http://vine.co/v/On1x6iUuwxK</a></td> <td>7,396</td> </tr> <tr> <td>9. <a href="http://on.rt.com/80mggq">http://on.rt.com/80mggq</a></td> <td>7,038</td> </tr> <tr> <td>10. <a href="http://bit.ly/1vFrMUx">http://bit.ly/1vFrMUx</a></td> <td>7,028</td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Top Image URLs:</strong></td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>1. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/B3qe80-CEAAWikm.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>11,453</td> </tr> <tr> <td>2. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/B3a_FyOCAAAmLxp.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>10,907</td> </tr> <tr> <td>3. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/B3S-EmbIcAEfEUB.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>10,681</td> </tr> <tr> <td>4. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/B3QPEpBCAAAD1c_.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>10,004</td> </tr> <tr> <td>5. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/B3ZzWTjIAAAkHwC.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>9,299</td> </tr> <tr> <td>6. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/B3Z-LUNCAAA_1P4.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>9,190</td> </tr> <tr> <td>7. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/B3YnVqyIgAA_8o9.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>8,484</td> </tr> <tr> <td>8. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/B3ginLnCIAEXnYD.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>7,870</td> </tr> <tr> <td>9. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/B3pa9UrIEAAhrmj.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>7,310</td> </tr> <tr> <td>10. <img src="http://pbs.twimg.com/media/B3SlDtxIIAARDT1.jpg" alt="alt text"/></td> <td>5,824</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p><br/> This is a pretty cool macro view of over 17 million tweets, and it can already tell us a lot about what’s inside these datasets. For instance, from these summaries alone, we can see #BlackLivesMatter emerging into the mainstream conversation about Ferguson. From August 10 to August 27, the hashtag #BlackLivesMatter doesn’t even make the Top 10. But by November, it’s rocketed all the way to <a name="bld"><a href="#blm">No. 4</a></a>. These four months were crucial for the rise and circulation of the hashtag #BlackLivesMatter, and this data helps tell part of that story.</p> <p>But of course this is not the <em>whole</em> story, and in fact it’s not even the whole Twitter story. After all, from the 13,480,000 tweet ids in the August collection and the 15,080,078 ids in the November collection, I was only able to hydrate 10,441,785 tweets and 7,868,540 tweets, respectively. That’s a lot of missing tweets. If you’re wondering where the heck all those tweets went, that’s an excellent question. If a Twitter user deletes his or her tweets before the time of hydration, that tweet gets lost forever. Poof! Ed Summers thinks this is a <a href="https://medium.com/on-archivy/on-forgetting-e01a2b95272#.jlm9fifcj">lowkey ethical move</a> on Twitter’s part, which allows users the right to be forgotten. Spam also gets routinely and retroactively deleted from Twitter, which also might account for some of the missing tweets. Even so, this is still a rather large gap, and I hope to theorize it more fully in later posts.</p> <p>For now, however, I’ll conclude Part 1 by saying that twarc is an awesome tool for creating Twitter archives if you know even a little bit about Python/the command line (though I should mention that Ed Summers is currently leading a project called <a href="http://www.docnow.io/">“Documenting the Now”</a> which aims to develop an even easier-to-use tool that requires no programming skills whatsoever) and twarc-report is a small but powerful utility for getting a sense of the contours of one’s dataset.</p> <p>In Part 2, I will discuss how I narrowed these collections to only the tweets that mention James Baldwin (by using jq and regular expressions) and show what the twarc-reports of these smaller James Baldwin collections reveal.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="twitter"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[So my project “Tweets of a Native Son” examines the way that Twitter conversations about Ferguson and the #BlackLivesMater movement invoke the literary author James Baldwin. What’s my archive? How did I build it?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Introduction: “Tweets of a Native Son”</title><link href="https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2016/tweets-of-a-native-son/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introduction: “Tweets of a Native Son”"/><published>2016-11-05T19:56:56+00:00</published><updated>2016-11-05T19:56:56+00:00</updated><id>https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2016/tweets-of-a-native-son</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://melaniewalsh.org/blog/2016/tweets-of-a-native-son/"><![CDATA[<p>I started this blog largely because I wanted to start sharing some thoughts and updates about my project “Tweets of a Native Son,” a large-scale computational analysis of tweets that mention “James Baldwin” in relationship to Ferguson and the #BlackLivesMatter movement.</p> <p>Like many other Americans, I was glued to my Twitter feed in August, 2014 as I watched the protests unfold in Ferguson, MO, just miles away from my home and university in St. Louis. The weeks and months following Michael Brown’s shooting revealed a rapidly developing relationship between social media, especially Twitter, and racial justice, as it provided new platfroms for organization, counternarrative, and conversation. As a literary scholar, I was particularly interested in the ways that people were invoking and quoting literature in their tweets about Ferguson and #BlackLivesMatter, particularly when they were invoking and quoting James Baldwin, which seemed frequently.</p> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">&quot;To be black and conscious in America is to be in a constant state of rage.&quot; - Baldwin <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ferguson?src=hash">#Ferguson</a></p>&mdash; deray mckesson (@deray) <a href="https://twitter.com/deray/status/511007888698253312">September 14, 2014</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <p><b></b></p> <p>What about Baldwin seems to resonate with our particular historical moment and this particular platform? Which of Baldwin’s texts and which kinds of texts—fiction, non-fiction, interviews, etc.—are being most frequently cited? What might this tell us about how Baldwin’s legacy is being constructed and used by readers? My project seeks to answer these questions and more by conducting a large-scale computational analysis of tweets about Ferguson and the #BlackLivesMatter movement, as well as a careful close reading of individual tweets and narrative patterns.</p> <p>The project is still very much in-progress, but I’m sharing my findings, thoughts, and continuing questions in this space. If you decide to follow along, I’d really appreciate feedback, so feel free to leave a comment below, email me at melanie.walsh@wustl.edu, or tweet me at <a href="https://twitter.com/MellyMeldubs">@mellymeldubs</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="twitter"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I started this blog largely because I wanted to start sharing some thoughts and updates about my project “Tweets of a Native Son,” a large-scale computational analysis of tweets that mention “James Baldwin” in relationship to Ferguson and the #BlackLivesMatter movement.]]></summary></entry></feed>